<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A resolution of certain queries concerning submission to the present government ... by a divine of the Church of England, as by law establisht.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21420</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12738542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12738542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 696:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A resolution of certain queries concerning submission to the present government ... by a divine of the Church of England, as by law establisht.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>(from t.p.) The queries: I. Concerning the original of government. II. What is the constitution of the government of England? III. What obligation lies on the King by the Coronation-Oath? IV. What obligation lies on the subject by the Oaths of Supremacy, &amp;c. V. Whether if the King violate his oath, and actually destroys the ends of it, the subjects are freed from their obligation to him? VI. Whether the King hath renounced or deserted the government? VII. Whether on such desertion the people, to preserve themselves from confusion, may admit another, and what method is to be used in such admission? VIII. Whether the settlement now made, is a lawful establishment, and such as with a good conscience may be submitted to?</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RESOLUTION OF <hi>Certain Queries</hi> CONCERNING SUBMISSION TO THE Preſent Government.</p>
            <p>The QUERIES,
<list>
                  <item>I. Concerning the Original of Government.</item>
                  <item>II. What is the Conſtitution of the Government of <hi>England?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. What Obligation lies on the King by the Coronation-Oath?</item>
                  <item>IV. What Obligation lies on the Subject by the Oaths of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. Whether if the King Violate his Oath, and actually Deſtroys the Ends of it, the Subjects are freed from their Obligation to him?</item>
                  <item>VI. Whether the King hath Renounced or Deſerted the Government?</item>
                  <item>VII. Whether on ſuch Deſertion the People, to Preſerve themſelves from Confuſion, may admit Another, and what Method is to be uſed in ſuch Admiſſion?</item>
                  <item>VIII. Whether the Settlement now made, is a Lawful Eſtabliſhment, and ſuch as with a good Conſcience may be Submitted to?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Divine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>As by Law Eſtabliſht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> April 8th, 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:93052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>THERE is no doubt but the imputation of Diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will, as the Viper that came out of the fire and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hand, be fixed on the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the Diſſenters of all ſorts; The Clamour is already very loud, <hi>Where is the Loyalty of the Church of</hi> England? Which though <hi>ad homines</hi> it might well be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, by demanding, <hi>Where is the Loyalty of the Papiſts?</hi> Whom the King had ſo far obliged, as to put them into the moſt conſiderable Offices of the Nation, excluding better Subjects; yet none of them, though they were well Armed, and in great numbers, ever ſtruck a ſtroke to defend the King againſt the Aſſailants, although by their miſchievous Counſels they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to thoſe unhappy Circumſtances. And the other Diſſenters, who pretended to be great numbers, and to have ſo great a Zeal for His Majeſty, for the favours granted them by the Indulgence, and ſhare in the Government, as with their Lives and Fortunes to aſſiſt him, yet were moſt forward to unite againſt him. But what have the Clergy done, to incur the Note of Diſloyalty? Did they enter into an Aſſociation againſt the King? Were they called in Convocation to declare their Judgments as to the preſent juncture of Affairs? Did they not as long as the King remained in his Kingdom obey him in all things Lawful, according to their Doctrine of <hi>Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience?</hi> It could not be expected that they ſhould take Arms, or expoſe their naked Bodies to the Invaders Sword. They kept their Stations, as their Duties to God and the King obliged them, committing themſelves to God, and waiting for his Salvation. And methinks when the Biſhops and Clergy were accuſed for Diſloyalty by ſome for not obeying the King in reading his late Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, which they could not do with a good Conſcience, and were generally applauded for ſuch Refuſal, they ſhould not now be decried for keeping to the ſame Rule, of not doing ſuch things, for which their Conſciences (till better informed)
<pb facs="tcp:93052:3"/>will condemn them. But we are now brought into a great ſtrait, in which our Adverſaries will by all Arts imaginable endeavour to keep us, and which way ſoever we turn, they will turn it to our Ruin, if it be poſſible. If we comply with the preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, they will rob us of our Reputation and Faithfulneſs towards the People committed to our Charge, as if we had miſled them, and taught them thoſe Doctrines, which we our ſelves never intended to practice. If we comply not, they judge us Men worthy to be deprived of our Livelihoods, and with our Families to be expoſed, as in the late War, to Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, and new Committees: Theſe are no groundleſs Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but real Fears, and in ſome degree matters of Fact; for almoſt in every Pariſh there are Perſons of different Perſuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and if the Miniſter pray for the preſent King and Queen, according to Order, one part of the Mobile condemn him for an Apoſtate from his own Doctrine, and a Rebel. If we keep to our Liturgy, which by Oath we are bound to do, (and tho' we have as yet no Order regularly tranſmitted to us for altering any of thoſe Prayers) there is another Party threaten to knock us on the heads, and great Affronts have been offered to ſeveral Conſcientious Miniſters on both theſe occaſions. What then ſhall we do to extricate our ſelves from theſe Mazes, which are daily enlarged, and become more dark and difficult; for 'tis not the caſe of a few Biſhops or private Miniſters only, but the caſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which if our Enemies can divide in this, they will eaſily deſtroy us, and not us only, but the whole Intereſt of the Proteſtant Churches abroad, whoſe welfare much depends upon our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Agreement in this Nation. It therefore concerns us all ſeriouſly and ſincerely to enquire after the due meaſures of Obedience to our preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, that doing our Duties according to the Commands of God, and the Dictates of a well-inform'd Conſcience, we may ſtop the mouths of ſuch as are opened against us, and ready to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us up. I ſhall at preſent only conſider</p>
            <p>The Objection against the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is,
<pb facs="tcp:93052:3"/>That ſhe hath Deſerted the King contrary to her Oaths, her own Doctrine for <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> and their Declaration for <hi>Non-reſiſtance, (viz.)</hi> That it is not Lawful on any Pretence whatſoever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer, 1.</hi> That the Doctrine of the Church, as to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Juncture, is not known but by their Determinations in a Convocation duly called: for what ſome of the Clergy do act or declare, is not to be imputed to the Church. In the War raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against <hi>Charles</hi> the First, ſome of the Clergy, as <hi>Sibthorp</hi> and <hi>Manwaring</hi> ſtretched the Prerogative too high, others, as <hi>Marſhal</hi> and <hi>Calamy</hi> (all which pretended to be of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) depreſſed it as low: But neither of theſe Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties could be charged on the Church which kept in a middle way. And under the late King ſome were of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Sibthorp</hi> and <hi>Manwaring,</hi> as the Biſhops of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Oxford;</hi> others refuſed to comply ſo far as to publiſh his Declaration: what the Church would have done in Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is a <hi>Non conſtat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> As to the Doctrines of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> which were not ſo generally taught; but others did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That thoſe general Rules might admit of just Exceptions, and had certain tacite Conditions and Qualifications in them, which in caſe of great alterations in the Affairs of Government, would appear to be neceſſary and juſtifiable; and they ſuppoſe that if ſuch a caſe as ours now is, had been thought of, or propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it would certainly be excepted or provided against. And they think it fit that the condition and circumſtances of the Times wherein ſuch Doctrines were publiſhed, ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, for from the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> we lived under Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes governing by Laws, and Defenders of our Faith, who though they erred from the Laws and the Honour of the Church in ſome leſſer matters, as the neceſſity of their Affairs and Counſels perſwaded them, yet as to the Fundamentals of both Laws and Religion, they reſolutely adhered to them; yet was there in the People ſuch a ferment of Rebellion infuſed by
<pb facs="tcp:93052:4"/>Malecontents perſwading them of great danger both to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Laws, that the People were alway ready to take fire from the ſparks of groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies, and at last broke forth into ſuch a flame as well nigh turned the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Aſhes: and this was done against a Prince who as much abhorred Tyranny and Popery, as any of his Subjects could; it was therefore neceſſary that when after twenty Years Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we were brought (as by a Miracle) to ſettle on our first Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, the ſtrictest Rules and Doctrines for Obedience ſhould be inculcated to the People. Thus by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when a Stick is crooked we bend it to the contrary part to bring it ſtrait; and the Rule is generally approved, <hi>Imquum petas ut aequum feras;</hi> To demand more than is due, that we may not receive leſs.<note place="margin">See his Sermon on <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4.</note> It is obſerved by Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> that both Moral and Political Aphoriſms (tho' delivered in general Terms) do need Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and admit Exceptions, elſe they would claſh with Reaſon and Experience: The best Maſters of ſuch Wiſdom interdict things apart, by unſeaſonable or exceſſive uſe to be perverted, in general forms of Speech, leaving the Reſtrictions which the caſe may require or bear, to be made by the Hearers or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters diſcretion, whence many ſeemingly formal Prohibitions are to be received only as ſober Cautions. So far that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctor. So Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi>'s Sentences delivered in general terms are not always intended to be taken in their full lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but to have their commodious reſtrictions according to the quality and nature of the matter in hand, P. <hi>5.</hi> of <hi>the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Princes.</hi> And in dangerous Cauſes, <hi>Abundans cautela non nocet,</hi> which may ſerve as a reaſon for our preſſing the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> in ſuch dangerous times as we lived in, in ſuch general terms. And if we ſhould collect all that the ancient Fathers have ſaid in the heat of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies and Diſputations, or in their Panegericks and Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, and compare them with their Dogmata or Opinions, when they wrote their mature Judgments of matters of Faith and
<pb facs="tcp:93052:4"/>Doctrine, we might find them to contradict themſelves more then the preſent Church doth contradict herſelf in theſe Doctrines of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi> Thus for inſtance, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> diſputing against the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> who defended Free-will, wrote as if he had been a <hi>Manachee,</hi> and defended an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible Fate; and when he diſputed against the <hi>Manachees</hi> he ſeemed to be a <hi>Pelagian,</hi> and to defend Free-will. And thoſe who are Predeſtinarians in their Writings, in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to the People, agree with the <hi>Arminians:</hi> And the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which ever ſince the Reformation taught the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> in any caſe whatſoever, have yet manifeſted their Judgment, that this general Rule may inſome caſes admit exception, as by the Aſſiſtance given to the <hi>Scots, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Proteſtants in defence of their Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as hereafter mentioned may appear. God himſelf reverſed the Sentence denounced in general terms against the <hi>Ninevites</hi> upon their performing of the tacite Condition of returning from their evil Ways, and yet there was no variableneſs in God: And if there be any ſuch tacite Conditions in the Laws and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Men, (as is confeſt by many wiſe and good men) the ſence of ſuch Law and Declarations may differ from the letter when the ſtate of Affairs doth alter; for if it had been foreſeen that a King ſhould ariſe that would exerciſe Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, and ſubject the Kingdom to the Pope, deſtroy the Religion and Properties of the Subjects (a caſe ſo odious and improbable that it could not well be ſuppoſed) the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> would not have been prest to thoſe ends) which were intended to the contrary,) <hi>viz.</hi> to make way for Popery, and Tyranny, and Confuſion, <hi>Tempora mutantur non nos;</hi> We adhere to our firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſtill, for, <hi>Levitas non eſt deſtituere ſi aliquid novi intervenerit eadem mihi Omnia praeſta, &amp; idem Sum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> But as to matter of Fact, let it be inquired what have the Clergy acted contrary to thoſe Doctrines: While the King continued in the Government, they continued their Obedience,
<pb facs="tcp:93052:5"/>even when their Liberties and Properties were actually taken away, and their Lives were at ſtake. Since the King's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, they have been under reſtraint, and an impoſſibility of defending him, whom the Nobility, Gentry, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and his own Army had generally deſerted, and joyned with the Invading Army; Hitherto then they have been Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; but the grand inquiry is, How they ought to behave themſelves under the preſent Circumſtances, (the preſent King in vindication of his Queen's Right, which was otherwiſe deſparate, and not to be recovered by Petition or Bill in Chancery, got full poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, and by a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Conſent in Parliament they are declared King and Queen) Whether our Allegiance be due to the late King, or the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Power under whoſe Protection we live and enjoy our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Laws, and Liberties which were ſo near to be loſt. Some men of great Reputation for Learning and Piety, think themſelves obliged by their former Oaths: And the preſent Government think they cannot be ſecure till the Clergy are obliged to them by new Oaths, the refuſal whereof may draw on Suſpenſion and Deprivation, to the undoing not only of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Families, but the Eſtabliſhed Church at home, and the Proteſtant Intereſt over all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> if any Wars or Diviſions ſhould be occaſioned by ſuch Refuſal: for Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, I earneſtly intreat my Brethren the Clergy to lay aſide all Prepoſſeſſions and Prejudices, and ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Anſwers given to the following Queries, which the Author hath collected from<note n="*" place="margin">St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> l. 3. Concerning Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſays, there are two ways of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Doubts, either by our own reaſon or the authority of the moſt learned. <hi>Nam qui conſiliis pollet ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ipſe, nec audit Suadentes alios, nullos homo vivit in uſus.</hi>
               </note> the Writings of men of great Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Learning, and Experience, partly for his own ſatisfaction, but moſtly for the ſatisfaction of others whoſe welfare is as dear to him as his own, that yeilding due Subjection to the King and Queen, and all that are now in Authority, <hi>we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The Original of Government in General.</head>
               <p>GOD is the Fountain of all Government, being not the Author of Confuſion but of Peace, and hath eſtabliſhed Order among all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; in the Angelical Nature he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted ſeveral Orders, Angels and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, Principalities, Powers and Dominions; in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Bodies, the Sun to rule by Day, and the Moon by Night, and one Star differeth from another Star in glory. And when he made the firſt man, he gave him dominion over all the works of his hands, he was to rule his Wife, and ſhe to live in ſubjection to him, and when he became a Father, his Children were to yield him obedience. And when the Families of the Earth were multiplied, ſo that one Father or Family could not claim Authority over the reſt, and conſidering the great corruption of Nature, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but Violence and Injuſtice would be practiſed, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſaw a neceſſity of ſetting up one Common Father over many Families, to ſuppreſs Violence, redreſs Injuries, and diſtribute Juſtice. To this purpoſe Mr. <hi>Hooker, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. Two Foundations there are which bear up Publick Societies, the one a natural inclination, whereby all men deſire a ſociable life and fellowſhip; the other an order expreſly or ſecretly agreed on touching the manner of their union in living together; for if when there was but one Family in the World, the means of inſtruction, Humane and Divine, could not prevent ſhedding of Blood, how could it be but when Families were increaſed, each providing for it ſelf, ſtrife, contention and violence muſt grow among them?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93052:6"/>To take away ſuch mutual Grievances, Injuries and Wrongs, there was no way but only by growing unto compoſition and agreement among themſelves, by ordaining ſome kind of Publick Government, and by yielding themſelves ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thereunto, that to whom they granted Authority to Rule and Govern, by them the Peace and Tranquility of the reſt might be procured — No man might in reaſon take upon him to determine his own right, therefore ſtrife and troubles would be endleſs, except they gave their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent to be ordered by ſome whom they agreed on, without which conſent there was no reaſon one man ſhould take on him to be Lord or Judge over another — and over a multitude of Families; impoſſible it is, that any one ſhould have compleat power, but by conſent of men, or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate appointment of God. All publick regiment of what kind ſo ever, ſeemeth evidently to have riſen from delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate advice, conſultation and compoſition between men judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it convenient and behoofful. And (the corruption of Nature preſuppoſed) the Law of Nature doth neceſſarily require ſome kind of regiment; and men ſaw, that to live by one man's will, became the cauſe of all mens miſery; this conſtrained them to come to Laws, wherein all men may fee their Duties, and know the Penalties of tranſgneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them. And tho' wiſe and good men are fit to make Laws, yet Laws take not their conſtraining power from thoſe that make them, but from the power which gives them the ſtrength of Laws. And by natural Law, the lawful power of making Laws, whereto all Societies are ſubject, belongs ſo properly to thoſe entire Societies, that for any Prince or Potentate of what kind ſo ever, to exerciſe the ſame of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and not either by expreſs Commiſſion from God, or Authority derived from their conſent, upon whoſe perſons they impoſe Laws, is no better than Tyranny; Laws they are not, which publick approbation hath not made. So far judicious <hi>Hooker,</hi> in as evident a manner as any demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93052:6"/>in <hi>Euclid,</hi> to which add that obſervation of Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Selden de Jure Nat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 106.</bibl> By permiſſion of Nature, it hath been granted, that whatſoever hath been by men joyned in ſociety, limited, forbidden, or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, that they are bound to keep, who have ſo conſented, according to the Conditions and Qualifications with which it is preſcribed, even as many as have, and as they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their conſent. But whence is it they are ſo bound? from the Authority of a Deity, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> of man's Superior, even in thoſe things the riſe of the obligation is derived, and therefore from ſome heads of the obligation of the Law of Nature.</q>
                  <hi>Lod. Vives,</hi> on <hi>St. Aug. de Civitate Dei, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5, 6. takes notice of the firſt words of <hi>Juſtin, (viz.)</hi> That <q>in the beginning the rule of Nations was in the hands of Kings, whom not popular ambition, but their mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate carriage, <hi>approved by the good,</hi> advanced to that height of Honor, on which he gives this comment, That the People elected thoſe Kings to themſelves, to be Guides, Governors and Overſeers of the Publick Intereſt, and they were not compelled to take ſuch a one as hapned any way to them, neither did Nobility or the ſeeking of a party carry it, every man's own private good, with the good of the Publick, was ſo dear and near to him, that it made him to make choice of none but the beſt.</q> And it is obſervable from <hi>Livy</hi> and other Roman Hiſtorians, that <q>their five firſt Kings were choſen by the Senate and People, and that <hi>Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Superbus</hi> was by them depoſed.</q> 
                  <hi>Neque enim ad jus regni quicquam praeter vim habe bat ut qui ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> populi juſſu ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus autoribus regnavit,</hi> to which that of <hi>Juvenal</hi> agreeth, ſpeaking of the People, <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Satyr</hi> 10. </bibl>
                     <hi>Qui dabat olim Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um faſces legiones omnia.</hi>
                  </q> In our Nation, when the <hi>Romans</hi> invaded the Land, the People choſe <hi>Caſſibilane</hi> their King. On the death of <hi>Hardicanute,</hi> the third <hi>Daniſh</hi> King, they choſe <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor; and on the death of <hi>William</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93052:7"/>the Conqueror, they choſe <hi>William Rufus,</hi> and of four that ſucceeded the Conqueror, not one had the right by neerneſs of deſcent.</p>
               <p>It is objected againſt this Opinion of Electing our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, That the People, having no power over their own lives, cannot give that power to any other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not the People that confer this power, but God, who by his Law hath given this power to all ſupreme Magiſtrates, <hi>That he that ſheddeth man's blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> The People are only a <hi>Medium</hi> of convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this power of the Magiſtrate to a particular perſon, God is the Author of the Magiſtrates power, to which the puniſhment of Murtherers is annexed; for the general Rule is, That the Magiſtrate ſhall bear the Sword for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of evil doers; and Capital puniſhment is in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes juſt, the People only apply this general Rule, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the power to be in ſuch a particular perſon, for the terror of evil doers; ſo that though I, being a private perſon, have no power over my own or another man's life, yet the Magiſtrate hath by the Inſtitution of his Office from God. St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 25.11. ſays as much, <hi>If I have done any thing worthy of death, I refuſe not to die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Ordinance of Government is from God and Nature, but the Species of it, whether by one or more, is from Men, and the Rule for adminiſtration, is by mutual agreement of the Governor, and thoſe that are to be governed, from whence probably that which by St. <hi>Paul</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, God's Ordinance, as to Government in general, is by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2.13. called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Humane Conſtitution, as to the particular Species, for ſo the Supreme Power is called, whether to the King as Supreme. As for the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archal Conſtitution, and a Lineal Deſcent by proximity of Blood, it is ſo near to an impoſſibility of finding out the right Heir to the firſt Father of a People, that we muſt let that alone for ever. And as for Conqueſt, <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93052:7"/>§. 16. ſays, <q>He that doth uſurp a Government, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward enters not into a Compact with the People, (as it is evident <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror did, who alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a right prior to his Conqueſt) nor is there any truſt repoſed in him, but his poſſeſſion is maintained by force; the right of War doth in this caſe ſtill continue, ſo that it is lawful in all things to deal with him as with an Enemy. And <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. §. 7. <hi>N.</hi> 3. It is to be obſerved, ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> That men did not at firſt unite in civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities by any Command from God, but voluntarily, and from the experience which they had, that private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies were unable to reſiſt any foreign force; from hence grew Civil Power, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> therefore calls a Humane Ordinance, though elſewhere it is called a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinance, becauſe God did approve thereof, as ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and convenient for the good of Mankind, but when God approves of a Humane Law, he muſt be ſuppoſed to do it as Humane, and after a Humane manner.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <p>Concerning the Riſe of our Government, <hi>which is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Query,</hi> I ſhall ſearch no farther than the Reign of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> called <hi>the Conqueror,</hi> who in truth diſclaimed that Title, pretending a right to ſucceed by a Grant from King <hi>Edward,</hi> and an Oath of <hi>Harold,</hi> who ſwore to preſerve the Kingdom for him after the death of <hi>Edward;</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> being dead, many of the Nobles invited <hi>William</hi> to take the Crown, but <hi>Harold,</hi> contrary to his Oath, aſſumes it; whereupon he reſolves to vindicate his Title by the Sword, the Pope ſending him a conſecrated Banner, and approving his Title, and ſhortly after his landing, ſlays <hi>Harold</hi> in battel, and marching to <hi>London,</hi> is proclaimed King; and crowned by <hi>Aldred,</hi> Arch-biſhop, taking the Coronation-Oath, which was injoyned by King <hi>Edward,</hi> and is the ſame in ſubſtance with that which is ſtill adminiſtred, and in the Title of his Laws, made in the fourth Year of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93052:8"/>Reign, he ſtiles himſelf Heir and Couſin to <hi>Edward</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor, <hi>Spelman's Councils, p.</hi> 619. and confirmed all St. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s Laws. And his Son <hi>Henry</hi> declares his Father's Title thus, <hi>Qui Edvardo regi Haereditario Jure ſucceſſit,</hi> Selden ad Eadmerum, <hi>p.</hi> 211. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, his Son, aboliſhed the <hi>Norman</hi> Laws, which his Father added, as <hi>Cooke</hi> in the <hi>Proeme</hi> to <hi>l.</hi> 3. of his <hi>Reports.</hi> Afterwards the Barons threatned King <hi>John</hi> to ſeize his Caſtles, if he would not confirm their Laws, which they did until they got the <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It appears then, that our Government is not an Abſolute Monarchy, ſuch as that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the ancient Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Wills declared by Edicts, had the force of Laws, as is evident from, 1. The Manner of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws, the Legiſlative Power being divided between Prince and People; And, 2. The Mutual Oaths and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations that paſs between the Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and becauſe<note n="*" place="margin">Quas vulgus eligerit.</note> no Laws oblige the Subject, but what are agreed on by Prince and People in Parliament. 3. Nor can any Money, without their conſent, be raiſed. And whatever Laws have been thus made in former Ages, and ſtand unrepealed, do reſpectively ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige both Prince and People in future Ages. So that when Laws are thus made, it is not in the power of Prince or People to annul them, but by the ſame Authority by which they were made; by which it appears, that the Legiſlative Power, which is a chief Property of Soveraignty, is not ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Prince, yet may he pardon the Perſons of ſome Offenders, and remit the Penalties in ſome Caſes, wherein <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex,</hi> which Maxim, as it leaveth in the Prince a power of diſpenſing with the rigor of the Law, as he ſhall ſee it expedient for the publick good, ſo it leaveth alſo in the Subject a liberty upon juſt occaſions, (as in caſes of great exigency, and for preventing of ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards and inconveniencies as could not be foreſeen or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93052:8"/>and might prove of noiſom conſequence to the publick) to do other wiſe than the Letter of the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. See <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Caſe of the Liturgy, <hi>p.</hi> 170. for which he gives this reaſon, <hi>(viz.) It may well be preſumed, that the Law giver, who is bound in all his Laws, to intend the ſafety of the Publick, and of every Member thereof in his due proportion, hath no intention by the obſervation of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Law, to oblige any perſon who is a member of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to his deſtruction or ruine, when the common good is not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably promoted thereby.</hi> Upon which ground it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reſolved by Caſuiſts, that no Conſtitution (meerly humane) can lay ſuch obligation on the Conſcience of the Subject, but that he may, according to exigency of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, do otherwiſe than the Conſtitution requireth. This leads me to the <hi>Third Querry.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <p>The <hi>Third Query,</hi> which is concerning the Obligation of the Coronation Oath, and the Oaths taken by the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, of which I ſhall ſpeak joyntly, becauſe the Obligations are relative and reciprocal.</p>
               <p>There cannot be a more ſolemn Oath than that which is taken by our Princes at their Coronation, to which the Prince is obliged as to the Matter of it before his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as the Subject is bound to the Prince, tho' not not crowned; the Prince is our natural and liege Lord, as we are his natural and liege Subjects, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> according to Law.</p>
               <p>The Oath, as I find it taken by King <hi>Charles</hi> Firſt, of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory, is this:</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Sir, Will you grant and keep, and, by your Oath, confirm to the People of</hi> England, <hi>the Laws and Cuſtoms to them, granted by the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>your lawful and religious Predeceſſors, and namely the Laws, Cuſtoms and Franchiſes granted to the Clergy by your glorious King St</hi> Edward <hi>your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93052:9"/>or according to the Laws of God, the true Profeſſion of the Goſpel eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom, and agreeable to the Prerogative of the Kings thereof, and the ancient Cuſtoms of this Realm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant and promiſe to keep them.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Sir, Will you keep Peace and Godly Agreement intirely, according to your power, both to God and Holy Church, the Clergy and People?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I will keep it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Sir, Will you, to your power, cauſe Law, Juſtice, and Diſcretion, in Mercy and Truth, to be executed in all your Kingdoms?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I will.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Will you grant to hold and keep the Laws and rightful Cuſtoms, which the Commonalty of this your Kingdom have; And will you defend and uphold them to the Honour of God, ſo much as in you lieth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I grant and promiſe ſo to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Lord the King, we beſeech you to pardon and grant and preſerve to us, and to the Churches committed to our Charge, all Canonical Priviledges, and due Law and Juſtice. And that you would protect and defend us, as every good King ought to be a Protector and Defender of the Biſhops and Churches under his Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> With a willing and devout Heart, I promiſe and grant my part, and that I will preſerve and maintain to you, and the Churches committed to your charge, all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Priviledges, and due Law and Juſtice, and that I will be your Protector and Defender to my power, by the aſſiſtance of God, as every good King in his Kingdom by right ought to protect and defend the Biſhops and Churches under his government.</p>
               <p>Then the King ariſeth, and is led to the Communion Table, where he takes a Solemn Oath, in ſight of all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93052:9"/>People, to obſerve the Premiſſes, and laying his Hand on the Book, ſaith, <hi>The things which I have before promiſed, I ſhall perform and keep. So help me God, and the Contents of this Book.</hi> Now an Oath being a high Act of Religion, and called the Oath of God, invoking him as a Witneſs and Surety for the performance, and a Revenger in caſe of Tranſgreſſion, ought not (but as Medicines) to be taken but in caſes of Neceſſity, with good Advice, and great Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, eſpecially in ſuch Solemn and Publick Oaths, the violation whereof the very Heathen do abhor. And what the Laws of the Church and People are, the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and the <hi>Statutes of Parliament</hi> do ſhew; to all which the Prince is ſworn, and thereupon the People declare their acceptance of him, and ſome Subjects of all Orders do him immediate Homage in the Name of the reſt. And by the Laws of God and Men, thoſe things that are Solemnly Sworn to, on expreſs Conditions mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually agreed on, do equally oblige both Parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <p>The Subjects Obligation is expreſſed in ſeveral Oaths, the moſt conſiderable are thoſe of Supremacy and Allegiance; from each of which the Perſon ſworn is under a double Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation; firſt and primarily to the matter of the Oath which concerns both Prince and People, which they are ſworn to defend: And ſecondarily, to the Perſons ſpecified in the Oath, whoſe Intereſt it is to defend the ſame, <hi>(viz.) the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors.</hi> The Oath of Supremacy was framed to aſſert the King's Supremacy, in Oppoſition to the Uſurpation of the Pope, wherein we promiſe, <hi>To bear Faith and true Allegiance to the King, his Heirs and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Succeſſors, and to our power to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Priviledges,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>granted or belonging to the King's Highneſs, his Heirs and Succeſſors, or united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> This Oath was brought into Form by King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. And the Parliament then declared, <hi>That it was a Declaration of the Ancient Right of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93052:10"/>the Crown,</hi> which doth not at all exclude the Right of the Subject, becauſe the admiſſion of that Uſurpation would certainly bring the Subject under the Yoke of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> which by this Oath they are bound to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to reſiſt, as they did in the Reign of King <hi>John,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Kings, of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>In the Oath of Allegiance, we ſwear, <hi>to bear Faith and true Allegiance to His Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors; and him and them will defend to the utmoſt of our Power againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever made againſt his or their Perſons: And do our beſt endeavour to diſcloſe to His Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, all Treaſons and Traiterous Conſpiracies, which we ſhall know or hear of to be againſt him or any of them.</hi> And we alſo Swear, <hi>That neither the Pope of himſelf, nor by any other means with any other, hath power to Depoſe the King, or annoy his Countries, or to give Licenſe to any of them to bear Arms, to raiſe Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to His Majeſties Perſon, State, or Government, or to any of His Majeſties Subjects, within His Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning theſe Oaths it is obſervable, Firſt, that they were both intended to preſerve the King and his Subjects from the Uſurpations of the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> contrary to their Ancient Rights, which were oppoſed and reſiſted not only by many of our Kings which were them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Papiſts, but by the Nobles and Commons when their King would have ſubmitted to them. And if they who were Papiſts did ſo reſolutely defend themſelves againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Uſurpations of a Pecuniary and Temporal concern, much more ought we, when not only our Liberties, but our whole Religion, as Proteſtants, is invaded. Secondly, That by theſe Oaths we are bound to defend them to the utmoſt of our power againſt all ſuch as ſhall offer any Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or Hurt to His Majeſty's Perſon, State, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of His Majeſty's Subjects. Thirdly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93052:10"/>it is mentioned in the Oath, that theſe Priviledges were granted or annexed to the Crown, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by the firſt Conſtitution, agreed on by Prince and People. Fourthly, Becauſe it is ſaid, that neither the Pope of himſelf, nor by any other means with any other, (which may infer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the King himſelf ſhould joyn with him, as King <hi>John</hi> did) may do violence or hurt to the State and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or to any of His Majeſty's Subjects; from whence I inferred, that the Subjects were primarily obliged to the matter of the Oath, and then to the King's Perſon, becauſe the King in Perſon may joyn with the Pope to do violence and hurt to the Subjects, in which caſe the Oath binds the Subjects to the utmoſt of their power to defend and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Rights and Priviledges, which for their better Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity were granted or annexed to the Crown, not for their utter ſubverſion; and it is incredible that any Prince would oblige his Subjects by Oath, to which he himſelf hath ſworn alſo, or that he would expect the performance of it from his Subjects, which he himſelf with all his power is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to vacuate and deſtroy. And in ſuch a caſe we muſt recur to the Law and Dictates of Nature for preſervation of our ſelves and the common welfare againſt unfaithful and cruel Men; for there is ſuch a Law Prior and Paramount to any particular Conſtitution, and for the end whereof all Government was inſtituted; this is always accounted <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culpata tutela,</hi> ſo Natural and Neceſſary, that it cannot be annulled by any Civil Conſtitution. <hi>Et qui ſe cum defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poſſit occidi permittit illum damnari poſſe non aliter ac ſi ſeipſum occidiſſet,</hi> he is a <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> guilty of Self-murder. And doubtleſs if it had been propoſed to the Law-makers, whether they intended to oblige themſelves to aſſiſt and defend the King's Perſon in caſe he ſhould joyn with the Pope and <hi>French</hi> King to ſet up the Inquiſition, and bring in <hi>French</hi> Dragoons, they would never have enacted ſuch a Law; and therefore we may preſume they never intended
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93052:11"/>ſuch Obligation. Fifthly, That we are bound to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them to the King and to his Heirs and Succeſſors, and him and them to defend to the utmoſt of our power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crown, or Dignity. Suppoſing then there be an Attempt made to deprive the Heir Apparent of the Right of Succeſſion, there is an Obligation on the Subjects not only to diſcloſe and make it known to ſuch Heir and Succeſſor, but him and them to defend to the utmoſt of our power. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> ſays, ſecond Vol. <hi>p.</hi> 137. <hi>Where the right of Succeſſion is in a Family by Law or Time immemorial, no Prince can prejudice his Heir, or the People committed to him, for it cannot without conſent be alienated, becauſe Perſons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſpoſed of as Slaves or Beaſts; ſo that in this (and ſome other caſes) the King loſeth his Authority, and then the force of the Obligation ceaſeth alſo.</hi> And how good an Opinion the Ancient Clergy and others had of the Peers and People that fought in defence of the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and againſt the Uſurpations of the Popes, may appear by the Writers of that and the ſucceeding Ages concerning <hi>Simon Montfort.</hi> The Chronicle of <hi>Meilrois,</hi> lately Printed by the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> p. 231. ſays, <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubuit cum multis ex magnatibus Anglicis qui venerant ad bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ut certarent pro juſtitiâ Angliae, cujus poſt modum Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae infallibile ſignum fuit crebra miraculorum exhibiti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutus exhibita circa Hugonem ſummum Angliae diſpenſato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem &amp; Simonem de Montfort, qui occubuerunt pro juſtitia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certentes &amp; idio nonnulli eorum meruerunt à deo miraculorum exhibitionem,</hi> of which Miracles they give divers inſtances. And long after theſe Writers, which lived in the time of the Barons Wars, <hi>Polidore Virgil,</hi> who lived in the days of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. gives this Teſtimony to <hi>Simon de Montfort,</hi> p. 317. of the <hi>Baſil</hi> Edition, <hi>Inhaeſit hominum mentibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans opinio hunc (Simonem de Montfort qui ob patriam &amp; jus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93052:11"/>jurandum</hi> (for it ſeems they were under the like Oaths) <hi>vitam amiſiſſent interiiſſe Martyrem id quod &amp; vita ſanctitas non patitur negandum, jam tum fueri qui ejus memoriam ut dici cujuſpiam colere ceperunt complureſque id feciſſent cui Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis iram non perti muiſſent.</hi> For if the Prince do evidently violate not only the Coronation-Oath, but act contrary to the tenor of the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, and actually ſubject the People to that Juriſdiction and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, againſt which they are ſworn, what is the extent of that Clauſe in the Oath of Supremacy <hi>(viz.) To our power to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, and Authorities granted or beloning to the King's Highneſs, &amp;c?</hi> Doubtleſs they that granted them, and by Oath are bound to aſſiſt and defend them being granted, may oppoſe ſuch as attempt the deſtruction of them, when not only the King's Prerogative, but the Peoples Religion, their Laws, and Liberties are aſſaulted, and in a way to be utterly ruined: And Treaſon may be committed againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as well as againſt the King; and alſo the King's Eldeſt Son. It is well known how reſolutely our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in the darkeſt times of Popery (being themſelves Papiſts) did defend the Nation againſt the Incroachments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when their Kings would have parted with this Right, which they affirmed he neither could nor ſhould do, and in defence of them they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of their Lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query.</hi> Whether theſe Premiſes being undeniable, the Subjects that according to their Oaths did timely endeavour (the caſe being otherwiſe deſperate) to vindicate as well the Right of the Crown to the King, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, as their own Religion and Liberties, did not act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Oaths and Duties, not by reſiſting their Prince, but by defending the Succeſſion and themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Inſtruments as acted contrary to the tenor of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93052:12"/>thoſe Oaths. If Judges, Juries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had performed in their ſeveral places as the Law and their Oaths obliged them, the King might have kept his Throne: We have a Maxim in Law, <hi>That the King can do no wrong,</hi> becauſe he is ſuppoſed to do all things by his Miniſters, and they to act all according to the Law: But when a King ſhall chooſe ſuch Miniſters as will act againſt the Laws, and defend them therein, there cannot be a greater wrong done to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <p>5. In Anſwer to your Fifth <hi>Query,</hi> which concerns the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Obligations between the Prince and the People by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe Oaths and the Declaration hereafter mentioned. It is to be conſidered (as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſays in the Caſe of the Engagement, <hi>p.</hi> 90.) <hi>That Allegiance is ſuch a Duty, as every Subject, under what form of Government ſoever, by the Law of Nature oweth to his Country</hi> (primarily) <hi>and conſequently to the Soveraign Power by which that Common-wealth is governed,</hi> (who is <hi>Caput Communitatis</hi>) <hi>as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the preſervation of the whole Body.</hi> And ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Obligation of Laws (which will hold alſo in the caſe of Oaths,) <hi>That if the intention of the Law-giver ſhould be underſtood preciſely of that particular, actual, and immediate intention of the Law-giver in making a particular Law, it will not hold true in all caſes, but there is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Law-giver a more general habituate and ultimate intention of a more excellent and tranſcendent Nature than the former, which is to have an influence into and an over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Power over all Laws</hi> (viz.) <hi>an intention by the Laws to procure and promote the Publick Good.</hi> The former inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bindeth where it is ſubſervient to the latter, or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with it, and conſequently bindeth in ordinary Caſes, and in orderly Times. But where the Obſervation of the Law by reaſon of the conjuncture of Circumſtances, or the iniquity of Times (Contingencies, which no Law-giver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93052:12"/>could either certainly fore-ſee, or if fore-ſeen, could not ſufficiently provide againſt) would rather be prejudicial than advantagious to the Publick; or is manifeſtly attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with more inconveniencies and ſad conſequents to the Obſervers, than all the imaginable good that can redound to the Publick thereby, can in any reaſonable meaſure coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail; in ſuch caſe the Law obligeth not but according to the later and more general intention only. Even as in the Operations of Nature, particular Agents do move ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily according to the proper and particular inclinations; yet upon ſome occaſions, and to ſerve the ends and intentions of Univerſal Nature (for the avoiding of ſomething which Nature abhorreth) they are ſometimes carried with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions quite contrary to their particular Natures; as the Air to deſcend, and the Water to aſcend, for the avoiding of vacuity.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Coronation-Oath, I ſhall add here what Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> l. 3. p. 144. ſays, <hi>That a Prince's ſwearing to govern by Laws is very ancient,</hi> of which he gives di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers inſtances, and ſays, <hi>Kings are bound by natural Juſtice and Equity, without Oaths, to do ſo, for they are not Kings unleſs they govern, and they cannot expect Obedience unleſs they tell the meaſures by which they will be obeyed; and theſe meaſures cannot be any thing but Laws, which are the will of the Prince, which when publiſhed to the People then they are Laws. If Kings be not bound to govern the People by Laws, why are they made? By what elſe can they be governed? By the will of the Prince?</hi> The Laws are ſo, which are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed that wiſe men may walk by them, and that the Prince may not govern as Fools or Lions, by chance or violence, and unreaſonable paſſions, <hi>Ea quae placuerunt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanda,</hi> ſaith the Law, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Pactis. If this had not been the will of the Prince, it had been no Law, but being his will let it be ſtood to.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 143. <hi>Whatſoever the Prince hath ſworn to, to all that he is obliged not only as a ſingle perſon,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93052:13"/>but as a King, for though he be above the Laws, yet is he not above himſelf, nor above his Oath, becauſe he is under God, and he cannot diſpenſe with his Oath and Promiſes in thoſe caſes in which he is bound: Although the King be above the Laws, that is, in caſes extraordinary, and matters of Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet is he ſo under all the Laws of the Kingdom to which he hath ſworn, that although he cannot be puniſhed by them, yet he ſins if he breaks them.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 149. he ſays, <hi>The Prerogative of Kings is by Law, and Kings are ſo far above their Laws, as the Laws themſelves have given them leave.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 143. <hi>The great Laws of the Kingdom do oblige all Princes, though they be ſupream: The Laws of the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians <hi>were above their Princes, as appears in</hi> Daniel: <hi>And ſuch are the Golden-Bull of the Empire, the Salic and Pragmatical Sanctions in</hi> France, <hi>the</hi> Magna Charta <hi>and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Right in</hi> England. That great Emperour <hi>C. de Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus</hi> l. 4. <hi>Digna vox eſt Majeſtatis regnantis legibus allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſe principem profiteri.</hi> A Sentence worthy of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of a Prince to profeſs himſelf tied to his Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pareto legi quiſquis legem Sanxeris,</hi> was the wiſe ſaying of <hi>Pittacus.</hi> And the diſtinction of the Directive Power of the Laws and the coerſive, is futilous; for a Directive Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is no power, and a Law doth not only direct but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige.</p>
               <p>Thus the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius, Tantum mihi licet quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; leges licet. Auguſtine</hi> l. 4. c. 4. <hi>De Civitate Dei, Quid ſunt Regna niſi magna latrocinia remota juſtitia quae eſt legum effectus.</hi> The intention of the Coronation-Oath is to oblige the King not to invade the Rights of the Subjects and the Eſtabliſhed Clergy; and it is ſworn to the Biſhops by whom the Oath is adminiſtred. And St. <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 225. ſays, <hi>Expectationem eorum quibus Juratur quiſquis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit non poteſt non eſſe perjurus:</hi> Whoever deceives the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of him to whom he hath ſworn, is guilty of Perjury. It may be ſaid that by the Church and Biſhops
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93052:13"/>the King might intend ſuch as were of the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; but the expreſs letter of the Oath is contrary, (viz.) <hi>With a willing and devout heart I promiſe and grant that I will preſerve and maintain to you, and the Churches committed to your charge, all Canonical Priviledges, and due Law and Juſtice, and that I will be your Protector to my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by the aſſiſtance of God,</hi> &amp;c. To this Evaſion St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> gives a check, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 224. <hi>Quacunque arte verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quis juret Deus tamen qui Conſcientiae teſtis eſt ita hoc ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit ſicut ille cui juratur intelligit:</hi> By whatever art of words any one ſweareth, God who is Witneſs of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, doth ſo take it as he to whom he ſweareth doth underſtand it. And Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> blackneth ſuch a practice with the Sin of Perjury: <hi>Alterum perjuris Genus eſt ubi recte juraveris non ſincere agere ſed novo aliquo exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitato commento (ſalius tamen verbis) vim juramenti declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; evadere,</hi> Praelet. 6. de Juramento ſ. 7. Such a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is contrary to the qualifications of an Oath, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear, The Lord liveth in truth, in judgment, and in righteouſneſs:</hi> And in a Prince that ſo ſweareth, the Nations ſhall bleſs themſelves, and in him ſhall they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: But how can they hope that he will puniſh Perjury in others, that is guilty of it himſelf? To this I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly add what <hi>Grotius</hi> ſays l. 2. c. 14. ſ. 4. <hi>de Jure belli, That Promiſes fully made and accepted, do naturally transfer a right, and this holds as well in Kings as in private men.</hi> Their Opinions therefore that hold that a King promiſing without a good cauſe, is not obliged, are not to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It was nobly done of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, when the Pope offered to Abſolve him of his Oath, anſwered, <hi>Who will ever truſt another, when they ſee by my example, that an Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can make void the higheſt Bond of Faith.</hi> See <hi>Eadmer</hi>'s Hiſt. <hi>p.</hi> 126.</p>
               <p>And where there are mutual Stipulations between Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with Conditions expreſſed, if either Party fail in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93052:14"/>the Condition ſworn to on his part, the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not bound to perform what he was ſworn to: So Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> p. 177. <hi>de Jurament. If</hi> Caius <hi>ſwear to give</hi> Titius <hi>an hundred Pounds on condition that</hi> Titius <hi>aſſign to him ſuch a parcel of Ground at a certain day, which</hi> Titius <hi>refuſeth to do,</hi> Caius <hi>is diſobliged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And p. 216. <hi>De Conſ. A Subject is not ordinarily bound to obey a Law that is very greivous to the certain ruine and deſtruction of himſelf and Family, unleſs ſome great Neceſſity or publick Danger do appear.</hi> And p. 202, he ſhews, <hi>That when the ſubject matter of the Oath ceaſeth, the Obligation al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ceaſeth;</hi> as when the ſtate of Affaires between the time of ſwearing and of performing the Oath is ſo changed, that if he that ſwore could have foreſeen ſuch a change, he would not have ſworn: As if a Father ſwear never to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Will wherein he had made his Son to be his Heir, and afterward his Son attempts to poyſon him, the Father may appoint another Heir notwithſtanding his Oath; the reaſon is becauſe the root of the Obligation, which gave occaſion to the Oath being taken away, the Obligation alſo is taken away. And it is a Maxim in the Civil Law, <hi>Ceſſante Cauſa ceſſat Lex; Grotius,</hi> l. 2. c. 5. n. 17. thinks no queſtion, but a King by a long continued permiſſion may warrant a People to recover their Liberty on a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption that the King hath left it to them, <hi>Grot.</hi> l. 12. c. 4. n. 14.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> gives us theſe ſhort, but uſeful Rules concerning Oaths, 1. <hi>If what we ſwear to, be ſimply evil, the Rule is,</hi> Ne ſit Sacramentum pietatis vinculum impieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. 2ly, <hi>If it hinder a greater good, then,</hi> Ne ſit ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pietatis impedimentum pietatis. 3ly, <hi>If the Oath be ſimply made, yet it doth</hi> Subjacere civili Intellectui; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7, 8. where God ſpeaks conditionally of plucking up and deſtroying a Nation, <hi>If that Nation turn from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ways, I will repent of the evil,</hi> &amp;c. The Conditions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93052:14"/>may exclude the event, and the Oath remain good; So that if the Prince to whom we ſwear do whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pervert the end of the Oath, and require us to act contrary to the ends for which we ſware, we are not obliged to obey him contrary to our Oaths.</p>
               <p>Theſe things premiſed, will lead to a full underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Declaration required in the Act for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, viz. <hi>I do declare that it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> This is only a declaration of a Man's private Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the beſt information which he hath at preſent; nor can any man ſuppoſe that the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is indefinite can reach to every Kingdom, and therefore may be falſe as to ſuch Kingdoms, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that of <hi>Poland,</hi> where in ſome caſes Reſiſtance is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and in our Nation where the Laws are made the meaſure of the King's power, becauſe as <hi>Baldus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil.</hi> 1.245. ſays, <hi>Clauſula deplentitudine poteſtatis ſemper intelligenda eſt de poteſtate bona &amp; Laudabili.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly,</hi> It may be dubious (or rather out of doubt) becauſe it is poſſible for a King <hi>exuere Regis perſonam,</hi> as in caſe of Reſignation, Deſertion or great Diſtraction, ſuch as the late King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who in his Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſlew divers Subjects; and in ſuch caſes Nature dictates that we may <hi>vim virepellere,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf againſt <hi>Saul.</hi> And the Depoſing of the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was approved, as by other Nations, ſo by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> particularly.</p>
               <p>So that this Declaration though in general terms, may admit of exception, (as other ſuch Declarations do, as when I declare according to the fourth Commandment, <hi>That it is not lawful to do any manner of work on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day</hi>) yet <hi>Periculum vitâ tollit Sabbatum,</hi> and ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93052:15"/>caſes of neceſſity may happen as may make ſome kind of Work lawful to be done on that day. And it is a good Rule in Law and Equity, that <hi>Omnia dicta quantum vis univerſalia equitatem admittunt interpretem:</hi> So when I declare according to the Apoſtle, <hi>That Children ought to obey their Parents in all things;</hi> the exception againſt things ſinful is underſtood. And if a King in his Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, committing ſeveral acts for the Deſtruction of his innocent Subjects may be reſtrained, ſo may ſuch a Prince, <hi>Qui Sobrius ad evertendam rempublicam accedit;</hi> If our Promiſe confirmed by Oath, be grounded on a condition whereto it related, that condition not being performed, makes the Promiſe void, <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>Gr. de J. Belli.</hi> Or if the quality of the perſon ceaſe, the Oath ſworn to that perſon, in relation to his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, doth ceaſe alſo, <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>n</hi> 18. Every Contract though ſworn, is to be underſtood with this reſerved condition, That matters continue in the ſame ſtate, but not if they be changed. <hi>A wiſe Man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, changeth not his Reſolution, all things continuing as they were at the time that he made it; nor can he be ſaid to repent, becauſe at that time no better Counſel could be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed than that he reſolved on,</hi> L. 2. c. 16. n. 27. <hi>Eadem mihi omnia praeſta &amp; idem ſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly,</hi> Nor can a man declare it to be a traiterous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in ſome caſes (though he himſelf do abhor it in other caſes) to take up Arms by the King's authority againſt his perſon, or againſt thoſe that are commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by him, becauſe ſuch Commiſſions may be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perſons that by Law are diſabled to take ſuch Commiſſions, or the Commiſſions may be forged, as in the late <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, or they may be extorted from the King, being under the power of his Enemies, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93052:15"/>in fear of his life; ſuch was the caſe of <hi>Edward</hi> the 5th, when <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> ſeized on his Perſon, raiſing a War, and granting Commiſſions in the King's Name. Suppoſe that his Mother, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who had then the Broad Seal brought to her by the then Arch-biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> had raiſed another Army, to free the King from the Uſurper's power, could this ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſtifie the Duke and his Party, or condemn the Queen and her Adherents?</p>
               <p>And what hath happened, may happen again: As in the Caſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where Commiſſions are granted to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who are unqualified, <hi>Query,</hi> Whether it may not be lawful for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that Nation to defend by Arms ſuch as by thoſe Commiſſions aſſault them, for the deſtruction of their Religion, Laws, and Liberties? So that notwithſtanding this Declaration, if there be Laws and Oaths, and certain contingent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whereof the Subject that makes the Declaration is ignorant, which do allow a defence of the Crown, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Laws, and Liberties; ſuch defence may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, notwithſtanding the Declaration, as in caſe it ſhould happen that the King wholly deſerts and renounceth the Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <p>Which leads me to anſwer your <hi>Sixth Query,</hi> Whether, it being granted, that the King's being ſtudiouſly bent on the Alteration and Subverſion of the Government eſtabliſhed in Church and State, do amount to a Renunciation of the Government?</p>
               <p>After that <hi>Grotius</hi> had urged all the Arguments he thought of for Non-reſiſtance, he thought fit to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Reader of ſomething, leſt he ſhould think, that he had offended againſt that Law (of Non-reſiſtance) when indeed he had not, and the Admonitions are theſe:</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93052:16"/>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Such perſons as are under compact with the People, if they offend against the Laws, may be reſtrained by force; And if a King abjure his Kingdom and deſert it, all things are lawful against him as against a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> for which he quotes <hi>Barclay,</hi> who was the greateſt aſſertor of Monarchy, who ſays, <hi>If a King alienate his Kingdom, or ſubjects it to another, he loſeth it; Grotius</hi> his words are, <hi>Si Rex reipsà tradere regnum aut ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicere moliatur quin ei reſiſti in hoc poſſit non dubito nam aliud est perium aliud habendi modus qui ne mutetur ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare potest populus id enim ſub imperio comprehenſum non est.</hi> Seneca l. 3. Controverſ. <hi>Et ſi parendum in omnibus patri in eo non parendum in quo efficitur ut non ſit pater.</hi> And <hi>Barclay</hi> ſays, <hi>A Kingdom may be lost, if a King be carried on to the deſtruction of the People; Conſiſtere enim non potest voluntas imperandi &amp; voluntas perdendi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>If the King have one part of the Empire, and the People another, the King attempting to deſtroy the Peoples right, a juſt force may be oppoſed, and this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I think to have place, although it be affirmed, that the power of War</hi> (or Militia) <hi>is in the King;</hi> for that is to be underſtood of foreign War, for he that hath right, hath power to defend that right. <hi>Grotius</hi> on <hi>Heſter</hi> 8.11. concerning the Edict which <hi>Mordecai</hi> procured for the <hi>Jews</hi> to defend themſelves, ſays, <hi>Jus naturae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit authoritate Regiâ,</hi> ſuppoſing they might have done it by the Law of Nature.</p>
               <p>And on thoſe words of his, <hi>Si Rex hoſtili animo,</hi> &amp;c. hath this Note, <hi>Jo. Major,</hi> in 4 Sentent. ſays, <hi>Non poſſe populum à ſe abdicare poteſtatem deſtituendi Principis ſi in deſtructionem vergeret.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93052:16"/>
               <p>So <hi>Bilſon, p.</hi> 520. <hi>If a Prince ſubmit his Kingdom to a Foreigner, or change the Form of the Common-weal, or neglecting the Laws eſtabliſhed by common conſent, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his own pleaſure, the Lords and Commons may joyn and defend the Laws eſtabliſhed.</hi> From whence I argue thus, that Prince who ſtudiouſly altereth the Form and Conſtitution of his Kingdom, as ſuppoſe from a mixed and limited Monarchy, to an abſolute, deſtroys the Species of Government, <hi>qua talis,</hi> and ſo loſeth it; for the introduction of the new Form, is the deſtruction of the old; but a King that declares, (and acts according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) that he will govern abſolutely, and requires his Subjects to acknowledge his abſolute power, doth <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> deſtroy that Species of a limited Monarchy which he had, therefore he loſeth that Monarchy. And what was acted in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and intended to be acted in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is ſufficiently known, and a full confirmation of this Argument. And 'tis the judgment of <hi>Grotius,</hi> that he that openly in word or deed profeſſeth himſelf an enemy to the whole Nation, (and the major and better part may carry that denomination) is in that very act preſumed to abjure and renounce the Government of it; for if ſuch a Prince ſhould proceed to execute all his ruining Deſigns, he would leave none of his People over whom he might reign.</p>
               <p>To theſe, I ſhall add another Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> That a Prince or People may yield up themſelves to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing power, as the men of <hi>Capua</hi> and <hi>Collatia</hi> did to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſo loſt all their authority. And that our King did ſo, may appear by disbanding his Army on the approach of the preſent King, and ſubmitting himſelf to his Guards: And as King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Jews. Intempeſtivum est nunc libertatem concupiſcere, olim ne ea amitteretur certatum oportuit;</hi> He ought to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93052:17"/>have defended his Dominion while he had it, it is too late to require what by dedition and dereliction he hath given up.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There are in Laws, as well as in Oaths, <hi>Caſus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſi,</hi> and tacit exceptions, which the greateſt prudence of men could neither foreſee, nor ſufficiently prevent; nor indeed were it a point of prudence ſo much as to name them, being things odious, or rarely contingent, as the caſe of a King's being lunatick, or otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of the Adminiſtration of his Office, which our Laws have not provided againſt. Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> p. 41. <hi>De Juramento,</hi> mentioneth theſe four. <hi>Si Deus permiſerit, quoad licet, ſalvà poteſtate Superioris Rebus ſic ſtantibus.</hi> 1. If God permit, as in the 4th of St. <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that if <hi>Caius</hi> ſwears to <hi>Titius,</hi> to pay him at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> on the <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> a Sum of Money which he oweth him, but is at that time confined to his Bed by a grievous Diſeaſe, or in his Journey is robbed of his Money by Thieves, in this caſe he is not guilty of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, becauſe <hi>Rei impoſſibilis nulla est obligatio,</hi> there is no obligation to a thing impoſſible; and becauſe all things are ſubject to the Divine Will and Providence: therefore in every Oath, by a Common Law, this Clauſe is to be underſtood, unleſs God ſhall otherwiſe diſpoſe. For this he quotes the <hi>Gloſſ. ad quest.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>B. Paulus, In omni voto vel Sacramento intelliguntur hujuſmodi gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rales conditiones ſi Deus voluerit ſi vivero ſi potero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Another Condition to be underſtood, is, if it be lawful, becauſe there is no obligation to unlawful things; as if a man ſwear to obſerve all the Statutes and Cuſtoms of a Corporation, he is bound to obſerve ſuch only as are lawful and honeſt.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93052:17"/>
               <p>A <hi>3d</hi> Condition is a <hi>Salvo</hi> to the power of a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, as when a Son ſwears to do a thing that is lawful in it ſelf, but his Father being ignorant of the matter, commands another thing, the doing whereof hinders the Son from performing what he had ſworn, the Son is not bound by that Oath, becauſe by the Divine Law, he is bound to obey the command of his Father; the reaſon is, becauſe the act of one man ought not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the right of another.</p>
               <p>The <hi>4th</hi> Condition is, if things continue in the ſame ſtate wherein they were, as when a man ſwears to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn a Sword that he borrowed, and the perſon of whom it was borrowed, grows furiouſly mad, he is not bound to reſtore it. So <hi>Seneca, l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Ben. c.</hi> 35. <hi>Tum fidem fallam ſi omnia eadem ſint me promittente. Si mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur fidem meam liberat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is highly reaſonable to preſume, that ſuch caſes may happen, which if the Law-givers could have foreſeen, they would not have made or paſs'd into a Law; and therefore it may be preſumed they will not exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Sanderſon, p.</hi> 166. <hi>de Conſ. When the Law for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids that to be done, which the Subject cannot omit without ſin, or commands that to be done, which he cannot do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, ſuch a Law doth not bind;</hi> for, 1. <hi>Rei illicitae nulla est obligatio,</hi> as when a Prince commands the Worſhip of a falſe God, <hi>Prior obligatio praejudicat poſteriori.</hi> The obligation to preſerve the Common Welfare is prior to our Allegiance to the preſent Governor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Falkner,</hi> in his Book of <hi>Chriſtian Loyalty,</hi> ſpeaks as much for the unlawfulneſs of Subjects taking up Arms againſt the King as can be ſaid, <hi>p.</hi> 372, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet <hi>p.</hi> 542. he propoſeth the caſe, <hi>Whether if a Supreme Governor ſhould, according to his own Pleaſure, and contrary to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93052:18"/>eſtabliſhed Laws and his Subjects Property, actually engage upon the deſtroying and ruining a conſiderable part of his People, they might not defend themſelves by taking Arms.</hi> And he inſtanceth in the <hi>Paris</hi> Maſſacre, where about 100000 were ſlain in cold blood, moſt of which were innocent perſons, never accuſed or tried by Law, which he ſays, was ſuch a cruelty as can ſcarce be paralel'd under <hi>Mahometiſm;</hi> And he grants, that if ever ſuch a caſe ſhould happen, it would have great difficulties. <hi>Grotius</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thinks, that in this utmost extremity, the uſe of ſuch defence,</hi> ultimo neceſſitatis praeſidio, <hi>as a last refuge, is not to be condemned, provided the caſe of the common good be preſerved.</hi> And he ſeems to grant, that this may be true, upon this ground, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that ſuch attempts of ruining, do, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> include a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the governing thoſe perſons as Subjects, (<hi>i. e.</hi> according to Law) and conſequently of being their Prince or King, and ſo the expreſſions in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>that it is not lawful on any pretence whatſoever,</hi> &amp;c. would be ſecured. Now <hi>p.</hi> 529. he quotes <hi>Barclay, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 212. ſaying, <hi>that a Prince, ſeeking the ruin of his People, is no longer King. Se omni dominatu &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatu exuit atque ipſo jure ſive ipſo facto Rex eſſe deſiit, l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 23. With whom he joyns <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 11. <hi>Si Rex vere hoſtili animo in exitium totius populi feratur,</hi> to reſiſt ſuch a one, is not to reſiſt a ſoveraign King, but him who ceaſeth to be ſuch, <hi>Conſiſtere ſimul non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt voluntas imperandi &amp; voluntas perdendi quare qui ſe hoſtem totius populi profitetur eo ipſo abdicat regnum.</hi> And, <hi>p.</hi> 531. <hi>Falkner</hi> ſays, <hi>On yielding ſuch ſuppoſitions,</hi> (to be true) <hi>I ſhall grant the Anſwer given to be true.</hi> To this purpoſe ſpeaks <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. §. 7. <hi>n.</hi> 2. treating of Reſiſtance, <hi>This Law ſeems to depend on the intention of thoſe who first entred into Civil Society, from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93052:18"/>whom the right of governing is transferr'd.</hi> Now if ſuch had been asked, whether they intended to impoſe a Yoak equal to Death upon all that ſhould reſiſt the Tyrannies of a ſuperior Magiſtrate, upon any account whatſoever? I know not how they could willingly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in the affirmative; for what in this caſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity would recommend, that may be received as a Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <p>7. But another <hi>Query</hi> is, Whether the King, being deſtitute of the aſſiſtance of his Subjects, leaving the Land in confuſion, two Armies being in its bowels, hath vacated the Government, and ſo it is neceſſary, that ſome other, to avoid Anarchy and Confuſion, be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſucceed? To this I anſwer, 1. That the King, even before his leaving the Kingdom, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Government; for it is undeniably affirmed by Civilians, whoſe practice is agreeable, That <hi>nolle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere,</hi> and <hi>renunciare,</hi> are terms equivalent, as when a man conveyeth an Eſtate with a Charge and Incumbrance upon it, he that will not accept of the Eſtate with the Incumbrances and Charge, though he would gladly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Eſtate, doth, in the judgment of the Law, and in all Equity, renounce his Title to it; for he muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it <hi>modo &amp; forma debitis,</hi> or not at all; whence I thus ground my Argument, He that is not willing to hold the Government of <hi>England,</hi> as conſtituted with certain Limitations and Conditions annexed, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructively renounce it. But the late King was not willing to accept or hold the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government as conſtituted and limited, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the ſequel of the <hi>Major</hi> is clear, becauſe <hi>Onus tranſit cum emolumento,</hi> and both Law and Equity do preclude a right to the one, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other; an entrance into the Government, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93052:19"/>the obſervance of the Condition, <hi>modo &amp; formâ,</hi> is ſo far from giving a right to it, that it is a renunciation of it. And the <hi>Minor</hi> is as clear, becauſe it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a Popiſh Prince, ſuch as ours was, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to govern the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, without one or more Popiſh Prieſts, without many Papiſts in Office, Civil and Military, and without ſubjection to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and holding correſpondence with him. So that if it ſhould be demanded of the King, (which yet needs not the having ſufficiently declared the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) whether he would accept of the Government, as by the Laws and Statutes againſt Papiſts is provided, his refuſal is a renunciation. And of this we have had plain demonſtrations: The King declaring to the <hi>Scots,</hi> that he had an Abſolute Power, and practiſing the ſame in <hi>England,</hi> by entertaining the Pope's <hi>Nuntio,</hi> ſetting up of Popiſh Biſhops, impriſoning the Proteſtant Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, entertaining Jeſuits and Papiſts in his Privy Council, and chief Offices, Military and Civil, the Charters generally taken away, <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge emptied of its Students, to make way for Papiſts, theſe were manifeſt indications of the ſubverſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; for as <hi>Ariſtotle, l.</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Polit. n.</hi> 112. <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus efficitur qui vi dominatur, Regnum est Imperium vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate Civium delatum at ſi quis vel fraude vel violentia Dominatur manefeſta Tyrannis est, &amp;l.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 87. <hi>Reges ſolùm volentibus imperant ſi nolentibus imperatur regnum eſſe deſinit.</hi> So that the King having firſt deſerted the People, and loſt their affections, and for this and other cauſes deſerted the Kingdom, and left it in confuſion, giving order to his General to disband his Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pay, many of which were Papiſts, and known Enemies to the Nation, from whom they feared great miſchiefs to themſelves; There being alſo another
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93052:19"/>Army in the Nation which became ſucceſsful, it was highly neceſſary that the Nation to avoide utter ruine, ſhould by their Repreſentatives freely choſen, convene, to conſult and agree upon a fit perſon for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Government; and whereas the perſon that headed the prevailing Army, was by good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence married to the Heir apparent of the Kingdom, if he not only by his own merit in preſerving the Crown, which otherwiſe had been loſt, but by Marriage of the right Heir, and with her and the <hi>Kingdom's</hi> conſent be choſen to a Conſortſhip in the Adminiſtration of the Government, it is no more than what <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> did require.</p>
               <p>Nor is it more than what was done in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, who having overthrown <hi>Richard</hi> the Third in Battel, was in a Parliament called by him, acknowledged their King; of which I ſhall give you the Hiſtory as related by my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> p. 10. of his Hiſtory, which may ſerve as a Preſident to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize what is now done, and leads me to the <hi>Eighth Quere,</hi> to which I ſhall anſwer firſt Hiſtorically, and then Rationally in Juſtification of the late Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>The Coronation of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh was on the 30th day of <hi>October</hi> 1485, and on <hi>November</hi> the 7th the Parliament met, in which (without reſpect to his Queen's Title, whoſe Coronation was deferred till al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two years after, (when danger taught him what to do) he obtained that the Inheritance ſhould reſt, remain and be in the King and the Heirs of his Body, not mentioning his right Heirs: ſo that the Entail ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rather a perſonal Favour to him and his Children, then a Diſinheriſon of the Houſe of <hi>York;</hi> and this being obtained, he married the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> on the 18th of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93052:20"/>
                  <hi>January,</hi> which was celebrated with greater Triumph and Demonſtrations of Joy and Gladneſs, than either his Entry or Coronation, which the King rather noted than liked; and he ſhewed himſelf no very indulgent Husband to her, though ſhe were Beautiful, Gentle and Fruitful. So great an Enemy he was to the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> that he cauſed Sir <hi>Will. Stanly,</hi> who had ſaved his Life, and ſet the Crown on his head in <hi>Boſworth-field,</hi> to be executed for ſaying, That if he were ſure that young man <hi>Perkin Warbeck</hi> were King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Son, he would never bear Arms againſt him.</p>
               <p>This Caſe ſeems much more unjuſtifiable than ours, for here the King and Parliament did not only ſet the Crown on the head of the Conqueror, but intailed it on his Heirs, without reſpect to the right Heir, whom he had not yet married, and for ought they knew, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended; of which his ſtrange carriage towards that good Lady, whom he confined to live with the Queen Dowager, her Mother, in <hi>London;</hi> but he kept <hi>Edward Plantagenet,</hi> the Son and Heir of <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> cloſe Priſoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> might give the Nation juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion, that he intended to Reign by his own Title, as Heir of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> or as Conqueror, without any reſpect to the Title of the Houſe of <hi>York;</hi> And he intended (faith the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>) that it ſhould be ſo believed, for to the Act of Parliament he added the Pope's Bull for confirmation.</p>
               <p>But in our Caſe much more Juſtice, Wiſdom, and Moderation did appear; the Title of the right Heir being united to that of our Deliverer, and the Crown intailed on the right Line; the preſent Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being by conſent, and in the name of the King and Queen, which was not obſerved in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh; and the conſent of the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93052:20"/>alſo obtained, who hath now a nearer proſpect of the Crown than otherwiſe ſhe could have hoped for.</p>
               <p>Nor is the making of the Convention a Parliament without a Preſident, for in the year 1660, when Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Monk</hi> had ſummoned ſeveral Members in the like manner, but not ſo free, there being many of the King's Party excluded, yet they were made a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the King, notwithſtanding any want of the King's Writs, <hi>Anno Car. 2di,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <p>And as to the Rational Part of the Anſwer, let it be conſidered, That a Nation muſt unavoidably run into Confuſion, unleſs ſuch a means may be uſed; for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Royal Line ſhould be extinct, there can be no fitter means to ſettle a Government, than by ſuch a Convention duly choſen, and the Agreement of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, who want only the Royal Writ to Summon them, and that not being to be had, the Nation may do what is in their power to prevent that Confuſion which the King's deſerting them, and carrying with him the Broad-ſeal, leaving two Armies in the midſt of the Nation, by reaſon whereof it might in a ſhort time have been as ill with us, as it is now with our diſtreſſed Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> made neceſſary; and Neceſſity hath no Law ſuperiour to it.</p>
               <p>This therefore may be an Anſwer to thoſe that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt the too great haſt in proceeding to a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before a Parliament could be regularly called by Writ, for conſidering the great Deſtraction of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the ill Circumſtances wherein this and the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> were: The delay of a ſpeedy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, might have unſettled us for ever; for the King having either deſerted the Government, or being driven from it, and another being fully poſſeſſed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93052:21"/>of the Kingdom, the common Safety would ſoon be deſtroyed if either the prevailing Power ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, or ſome perſon not be admitted for the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice, and Prevention of Violence: As when a Ship maſter forſakes his Ship in a Storm, and his Mate thruſts himſelf into his Office, to guide the Ship, if the Mariners will not preſently obey him, as long as he guides the Ship towards the Harbor, the Ship muſt likely periſh, and the Mariners in it: Or if the right Maſter ſhould be utterly diſabled by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Deſtraction to perform his Office, may not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſume his Office by conſent of the Mariners? 'Tis King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's ſaying, <hi>The King is for the Commonwealth, and not the Commonwealth for the King:</hi> The end is alway accounted more noble than the means. And unleſs it ſhould be granted, that a King in plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Poſſeſſion ought to be acknowledged and obeyed, I cannot ſee on what ground our Saviour commanded <hi>Tribute to be given to</hi> Caeſar, or the Apoſtle injoyned <hi>Subjection to the Higher Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Powers then in being, being ſuch as uſurped on the Senate, and were ſet up as Emperours by a part of the Souldiary, their beſt Title being the Approbation of the Senate, <hi>Ex post facto:</hi> The Uſurpation of <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caeſar</hi> is too well known to need a Relation; and that could not give a ſufficient Title to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> againſt the Claim of the Senate: the Argument of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour for paying him Tribute, was, becauſe the Money bore his Image; as alſo the Money in the days of <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caeſar</hi> bore his, and ſo may be an argument for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribute to any Prince whoſe Money is current in a Nation. But this will be more evident by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who was the Prince in being when the Apoſtle wrote his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> which was either <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93052:21"/>Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Nero:</hi> and the moſt credible Hiſtorians inform us, that on the death of <hi>Caligula,</hi> the Conſuls and Senate adviſed how they might reſtore their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth to its ancient Freedom, taken from them by the <hi>Caeſars;</hi> but being too ſlow in their Reſolutions, becauſe of Diſſentions among themſelves, it hapned in the interim, that <hi>Claudius</hi> having hid himſelf, being frighted with the news of <hi>Caligula</hi>'s death, was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by a common Souldier, who knowing him, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted him Emperour, and led him forth to his fellow-Souldiers, with whom he remained a part of the night, <hi>Minore ſpe quam fiduciâ,</hi> ſaith <hi>Suetonius,</hi> the Conſuls and Senate then ſitting in the Capitol conſulting for their common Liberty, ſent for him by the Tribune of the People, to have his Advice therein; the Souldiers and People aſſembled, deſired that one might be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with named for their Emperour; on which <hi>Claudius</hi> took courage, and promiſing Rewards to the Souldiers, being alſo pittied by the People, who thought him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſuffer puniſhment, they ſaluted him Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives alike relation of <hi>Nero</hi> his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, <hi>Annal,</hi> l. 12. That <hi>Agrippina</hi> his Mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing for a time the death of <hi>Claudius,</hi> kept the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Gates ſhut, and pretended great kindneſs to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicus</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Claudius,</hi> until ſhe had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make <hi>Nero</hi> Emperour; and having gotten the <hi>Praefect</hi> of the Bands then on the Guard to her Party, ſends out <hi>Nero,</hi> accompanied by <hi>Burrhus</hi> to the Guards, where while ſome expected <hi>Britannicus</hi> to follow, the <hi>Praefect</hi> and Souldiers, to whom Rewards were promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſaluted <hi>Nero</hi> Emperour. Now one of theſe thus advanced to the Empire, by the Souldiers, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the Emperour then in being, when the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> was written, to whom Obedience
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93052:22"/>is required for Conſcience ſake, as to the Ordinance of God; if it be replied, that the Senate did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confirm them in the Empire, that will not vary the preſent Caſe, the preſent King and Queen being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confirmed by Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <p>That which hath been ſaid, leads me to conſider theſe Scriptures which ſeem to confine our Obedience only to the lawful Powers, yet ſome learned and good men have given ſuch a ſence of them as may raiſe a doubt, whether they ſpeak of a King <hi>de Jure</hi> only, or <hi>de Facto;</hi> and if of a King <hi>de Jure</hi> only, then of ſuch a one as is a Miniſter for the publick Good only.</p>
               <p>For a right underſtanding of thoſe Scriptures of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> which ſpeak of Obedience to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.13. We are to conſider the occaſions of inditing them; that of our Saviour was occaſioned by ſuch as accuſed him for any Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he would make himſelf a King, and ſought by this queſtion to inſnare him, which our Saviour perceiving, he only demands to ſee a piece of the Money with which they traded; and finding <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image on it, conceived him to be the Magiſtrate then in power, commands <hi>to give unto Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar the things that are Caeſar's.</hi> Moreover, the <hi>Jews</hi> having from the beginning been governed by one of their Nation, and, as they boaſted, never in Subjection to any other, thought it an Uſurpation in any to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Dominion over them, which made the <hi>Roman</hi> Power very jealous of them, there being at that time great expectation of a Prince that ſhould Govern the World; and the frequent Seditions and Rebellions of that Nation againſt their own and the <hi>Roman Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> increaſed theſe Jealouſies; <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made a great Inſurrection, and the Chriſtians
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93052:22"/>being called <hi>Galileans,</hi> were thought to be of the ſame Spirit.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that were converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, to which they were invited partly by the Priviledges of their Chriſtian Liberty, that they ſhould not be the Servants of Men, and partly by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Prohibition of going to Law before Unbelievers, ſome weak, and others licentious as the <hi>Gnoſtiks,</hi> would acknowledge no Magiſtrates; and as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, ſome of the <hi>Galileans</hi> would rather die than pay Tribute to the <hi>Romans.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath divers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on this 13 <hi>Romans</hi> very conſiderable; firſt he ſtops the mouths of ſuch as did object, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle did abaſe his Chriſtian Brethren, by ſubjecting them to Earthly Princes, for whom the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Heaven was prepared: To this the anſwer is, That the Apoſtle did not ſo much ſubject them to thoſe Princes as to God, who appointed them. Then he raiſeth a queſtion, <hi>Is every Prince then ordained of God?</hi> I ſay not ſo, for I ſpeak not now of any Prince, but of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter itſelf: for that ſome ſhould command and others obey, this I call the Ordinance of God; and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains his meaning by the inſtance of Marriage, that the Man and Woman are joyned by God, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is God's Ordinance; not that all ſuch as cohabit as Man and Wife are joyned by God, but only ſuch as are married according to the Laws of Wedlock: Thus the Apoſtle doth not ſay there is no Prince but of God, but there is no Power but of God. And on <hi>v.</hi> 5. for Conſcience ſake, he thus comments, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; That they might not be ungrateful to their Benefactors. So St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> from whoſe Comment we may obſerve, that although Government be God's Ordinance, yet the perſon in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93052:23"/>Government is not always ſo; he only is God's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who doth adminiſter the Government for the common Good. 2. That we owe Subjection to the perſon inveſted with the Government, who takes care for the publick Welfare, for Conſcience ſake; <hi>(i. e.)</hi> as an acknowledgement of the Benefits that we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of under his Adminiſtration of the Government: Nor doth it appear, that our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. did determine that <hi>Caeſar</hi> was the Supeme Power <hi>de Jure;</hi> for if in a private caſe he refuſed to decide a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted right, <hi>Who made me a Judge or Divider over you? Luke</hi> 12.14. much leſs is it probable that he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to determine ſuch a publick caſe. And that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had no other reſpect but to the perſon in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the preſent Power, may be doubted from what followeth:</p>
               <p>As for the Obſervation of ſome Criticks, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is conſtantly uſed for a Perſon in Lawful Authority, we find it otherwiſe; for St. <hi>Luke,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>of the power of darkneſs, (i. e.)</hi> the Devil, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.53. his words are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the power of the Devil. Nor could the Devil derive a Lawful Authority, as he could, if this word would bear it, when ſpeaking of the Kingdom of the World, he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>all this power will I give thee;</hi> as if he had power to ſet up an univerſal Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror over the World. And St. <hi>Luke</hi> is obſerved to have written moſt exactly agreeable to the <hi>Greek</hi> Idium of any of the Evangeliſts. So that it cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from this Scripture, that the Perſons then in Power were rightful Magiſtrates. <hi>Grotius de Jure Belli,</hi> p. 93. c. 4. § 20. <hi>In re controverſa Judicium ſibi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus ſumere non debet ſed poſſeſſionem ſequi ſic tributum ſolvi Caeſari Chriſtus jubet,</hi> Matth. 22.20. <hi>quia in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſione
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93052:23"/>erat Imperii &amp; nummus ejus habuit imaginem:</hi> From whence it followeth in the judgment of <hi>Grotius,</hi> that our Saviour's Command to pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was grounded on his being in poſſeſſion of the Empire. And if this be ſo, as I cannot from the Command of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. or from <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. ſee any Reaſon to the contrary, it will follow, that it is our Duty <hi>in licitis &amp; honeſtis</hi> to yield Obedience to the preſent Powers. <hi>Michael Salon,</hi> an eminent School-man, is of the ſame Opinion, <hi>That the</hi> Romans <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> Judea <hi>by Tyranny, when our Saviour enjoyned the paying of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> Q. 60. Art. 6. <hi>de juſtitiâ &amp; Jure;</hi> where yet he affirms, <hi>That the Catholicks of</hi> England <hi>were bound to obey the juſt Laws of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>whom he calls an impious Woman.</hi> Beſides, I think it will be a very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Task for any Man to ſhew where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is applyed to any Perſon that is out of the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Power, ſeeing it ordinarily ſignifieth the Perſon that is actually in poſſeſſion of the Power. For thus the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Powers that are in being, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and to them he ſays we muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not only for fear of wrath, which implyeth that we ought to prevent our Ruin, to obey the Power that is in poſſeſſion. But then the Queſtion is, how this obligeth the Conſcience, when the Subject is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly obliged to a Prince <hi>de Jure?</hi> Now the Rule for directing Conſcience, is the Word of God, and if that do enjoyn Obedience to the Prince in poſſeſſion, the Subject may ſafely yield it, and ought to do it for Conſcience-ſake. <hi>Puffendorf</hi> is of the ſame judgment, <hi>p.</hi> 1009. <hi>de Jure Gentium,</hi> where he ſays, <hi>That the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and People of</hi> Rome <hi>were deprived of their Ancient Right through fear or want of ſtrength, not by approving the Dominion of the</hi> Caeſars. (So <hi>Emanuel Theſaurus</hi> ſays,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93052:24"/>that the People of <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Tiberius,</hi> did <hi>tempori ſeraire non Regi.</hi>) <hi>And it is well known</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by what means the ancient</hi> Caeſars <hi>invaded the Empire;</hi> yet St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. attributes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Authority to them to whom Obedience is to be yielded for Conſcience<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, as our Saviour alſo Commands <hi>to give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s.</hi> On which occaſion alſo he mentioneth that Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnifieth thoſe Subjects which acted under the King in being. And he adds a Sentence from <hi>Nicetas Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niates, nec Imperatorem qui abſit quaerendum, nec qui adſit pellendum eſſe.</hi> So that I think the Caſes in the 22 of <hi>Matth.</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. may ſatisfie Conſcience as to our preſent caſe; for if thoſe <hi>Caeſars</hi> who were then in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, were to be obeyed for Conſcience-ſake, even then when the Right did belong to the Senate, then we may alſo obey the King now in being, tho' there be another to whom it is ſuppoſed the Right of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment doth belong, without wounding our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
               <p>Now if the preſent Power be God's Ordinance, we muſt obey for Conſcience's ſake; for if we believe that God hath an over-ruling Providence in the Government of the World, to ſet up one, and pull down another, though we ſee not a Reaſon of the Alterations that are made, yet we muſt believe that there are great and juſt cauſes, and ſuch as are directed to good ends, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where it appears that God by ſuch Revolutions brings Order out of Confuſion; and the changes that are made, are effected more viſibly by the Counſel of God, than Conduct of Man. Another Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is the Glory of God, that which tends moſt to the advancing of God's preſcribed Worſhip, the purity of his Ordinances, a ſound Faith, and holy Life, we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93052:24"/>may with a good Conſcience ſubmit to. It is a ſaying of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> when he was near his Martyrdom, <hi>We owe all due Obedience to Princes and Potentates, yet not ſo as thereby to endanger our eternal Salvation.</hi> The Law of Charity is another Rule of Conſcience, which as it obligeth us to do good unto all men, ſo more <hi>eſpecially to them that are of the houſhold of Faith,</hi> for whom we ſhould lay down our very lives, that we may prevent their miſery and deſtruction. St. <hi>Paul</hi> could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>accurſed from Chriſt for his brethren and kinſmen, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 9.3. And what he ſuffered and did for his Brethren according to the Faith of Chriſt, appears as by his great Afflictions, ſo by his ready complyance in the caſe of Circumciſing <hi>Timothy, Acts</hi> 16.3. becauſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> which were at <hi>Lyſtra</hi> and <hi>Iconium,</hi> though he were of a Perſuaſion that Chriſt could profit them nothing that were circumciſed, ſeeing that ſuch became debtors to do the whole Law. And <hi>Acts</hi> 21.23. when St. <hi>James</hi> and the Elders informed him, that the <hi>Jews</hi> would be offended by his teaching them, that they ought not to Circumciſe their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor to walk after their Cuſtoms; he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, leſt he ſhould offend them, to purifie himſelf, and in the Company of others to go into the Temple, to ſhew that he kept the Law. From whence we learn, that it is out Duty to part with many Opinions of our own, not abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, for the propagation of the true Religion. I ſpeak not this as if it were Lawful to do any evil that good may come of it, which the Apoſtle utterly condemns, but only on ſuppoſition that the late King hath rendred himſelf uncapable of the Government, and that the preſent King and Queen (conſidering the Circumſtances where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we were) are regularly advanced to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93052:25"/>that we ought to pay our Allegiance to them. The Queſtion whether Humane Laws do bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is much diſcourſed of by Divines, who reſolve, that they do not bind the Conſcience immediately by their own Authority, but mediately by vertue of the Command of God, who enjoyns Obedience to the Higher Powers: But then if the matter of the Law be unjuſt, or if it be not for the Publick Good, which is the end of all Humane Laws, they are not Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Conſcience; for the Rule for Conſcience in things Political is the Publick welfare: So the Ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Law, <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex,</hi> which is the ſame with that of the Apoſtle, <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good, (i. e.)</hi> not for thy Private Good only, but for the Publick Good, attending continually on this very thing, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Publick Good, wherein thy Private Good is concerned; for the Laws do not reſpect this or that particular man's caſe, but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good; and good Laws may be grievous to this or that particular Man in ſome caſes, which yet highly conduce to the Publick Welfare, and better is a private Inconvenience than a publick Miſchief. Thoſe Laws therefore that tend moſt to the Publick welfare, are the Rule of Conſcience in Political Affairs. And for the ſame Reaſon that when a Magiſtrate makes a Law againſt God's Law in Religious Matters, it doth not bind the Conſcience: For the ſame Reaſon, when a Magiſtrate makes a Law againſt the Publick welfare, it doth not bind the Conſcience in Political Affairs: The Reaſon is, becauſe the Magiſtrates Power is derived from God, and God hath limited and determined that Power for the Publick Good as its great end, and ſuch Laws as are contrary to that end, have no Authority, nor do oblige the Conſcience. It is truly ſaid, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93052:25"/>ſome things are commanded, becauſe they are good; other things are good, becauſe they are commanded: Now our Obedience to Governors is good, becauſe it is commanded; but a reſpect to the Publick welfare in all Laws is commanded, becauſe it is the chief good and end of Government, and ſo is Prior and Paramount to all Politick Laws; and hence it is, that the Caſuiſts do reſolve, that Humane Laws do not bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when things grievous and intolerable are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. But then the Queſtion will be, Who ſhall judge whether the Laws made are conducing to the Publick Good or not, when not only the Magiſtrate, but the Repreſentatives of the People have pre-judged it, and therefore paſt it into a Law? <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are few Laws, like thoſe of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable; what was for the Publick Good at the time of making the Law, may afterward, on the alteration of Times and Accidents, prove to be otherwiſe; and when the Reaſon of a Law ceaſeth, the Obligation of it ceaſeth alſo as to Conſcience. There was a Law made againſt the uſe of that pernicious Weed of <hi>Hops</hi> (as the Law termeth it) becauſe it was thought prejudicial to the Health of the Subject; and though the Reaſon of the Law might be good as to ſome particular Men, Yet long Experience taught, that the uſe of <hi>Hops</hi> was more beneficial to the Publick; and therefore though that Law was not repealed, yet the uſe of <hi>Hops</hi> was continued: Now the Queſtion is, whether ſuch Brewers as continued the uſe of <hi>Hops</hi> againſt the Statute, did ſin or not in ſo doing? If they did not ſin, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Conſciences were not obliged by that Law; if they did ſin, then the breach of a miſtaken and erroneous Law is a ſin, and damnable, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard Sentence.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93052:26"/>
               <p>But Secondly, Although the greater part of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with their Legiſlators may judge the Laws made to be for the Common good, yet every Man muſt judge of his own Actions, in reference to thoſe Laws, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be agreeable to the Common good or no, for the greater number in Councils may err, there is no Infallible Judge in Civil or Religious matters: If then the Law-givers may err, or my Conſcience tells me that they do err, I am not bound to do what they Command by a blind Obedience, but to uſe my private diſcretion, in enquiring whether the thing enjoyned be for the Publick good or not; for if I am allowed to uſe the judgment of my private diſcretion in Religious matters, why not in Civil? Men are not to go as Beaſts where they are driven, much leſs to act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Reaſon and Judgment, which makes them worſe than Beaſts, who will follow their Senſes unleſs they are hindred by force; ſo that I am not bound to obey a Law meerly Humane for Conſcience<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, when I judge that Law contrary to the Publick welfare, but I muſt ſubmit to the Penalty, if I cannot honeſtly avoid it. But if a Magiſtrate that is obliged to govern by Laws, do reſolutely ſet himſelf to deſtroy thoſe Laws, and ruin not only the generality of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but his own Crown and Dignity, we are not bound in Conſcience to obey ſuch a Magiſtrate, becauſe of a prior Obligation to preſerve the publick welfare, which was the end of Government, and to which the means are ſubordinate. It now remains, that having proved that Scripture and right Reaſon to be the Rule of Conſcience for our Obedience both to Magiſtrates and their Laws <hi>in foro interno,</hi> that I do alſo prove, that a reſpect to the Publick good (not being contrary to any Law of God) is our Rule for Obedience, <hi>in foro externo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93052:26"/>
               <p>One chief Law imprinted by God on the Reaſon of Mankind, is the conſervation of it ſelf, and for that end <hi>vim vi repellere,</hi> to repel Force by Force, for which end Mankind were taught to live in Societies, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Rules and Laws for the Common Safety; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>homines conſpirantes in communem utilitatem,</hi> are the Subject-matter of a Common-wealth, this being the end of all Societies; no Civil Conſtitution can annul this Bond of Nature: So <hi>Panormitan, Quando jus Civile aliquid diſponit contra jus naturae ſtandum eſt Juri naturae.</hi> So alſo when the Law makes proviſion for ſuch things as the Law-givers fore-ſee, and afterwards ſome things happen which could not be fore-ſeen, and new Reaſons and Accidents appear contrary to thoſe Laws, here Nature, as a common Parent and Protector of Juſtice and Neceſſity, alters or adds to the Law; as when <hi>Sextus Tarquinius</hi> raviſhed <hi>Lucretia,</hi> though there were no eſtabliſhed Law againſt that particular ſin, yet Nature it ſelf directed a ſevere Puniſhment: And when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> pleaded their Vows to the <hi>Corban,</hi> in bar to relief of their Parents, which is a Law of Nature, our Saviour pronounced ſuch Vows null. Biſhop <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> p. 296. proves, <hi>That the Law of Nature cannot be diſpenſed with by any Humane Power:</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe God is the Author of it.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe this Law of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Common welfare is as neceſſary to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Societies, as Nouriſhment is for the ſupport of their Bodies.</hi> 3. <hi>Becauſe Natural Laws are the dictates of Natural Reaſon; and no man hath power to alter Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is an Image of the Divine Wiſdom, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unalterable.</hi> As to the Law part, the <hi>Act</hi> 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1. ſays, <hi>That it is not reaſonable, but againſt all Laws, Reaſon, and good Conſcience, that Subjects going in War with their Soveraign Lord</hi> (for the time being) ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93052:27"/>loſe or forfeit any thing for doing their Duty and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Allegiance; and it was Enacted, <hi>That from thenceforth no Perſon attending on the King for the time being, and doing him true and faithful Service of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance in his Wars, ſhould in no wiſe be convict or attaint of High Treaſon, nor of other Offence for that cauſe, but to be for that Service utterly diſcharged of any vexation, trouble, or loſs.</hi> The Lord <hi>Bacon, p.</hi> 144. of his Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. gives a Reaſon of this Law; <hi>For that it was agreeable</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to reaſon of State, that the Subject ſhould not enquire of the juſtneſs of the King's Title or Quarrel; and it was agreeable to good Conſcience, that whatever the Fortune of the War were, the Subject ſhould not ſuffer for his Obedience.</hi> The Spirit of this Law was wonderful Pious and Noble, being like in matter of War to the Spirit of <hi>David,</hi> in matter of Plague, who ſaid, <hi>If I have ſinned, ſtrike me, but what have theſe Sheep done?</hi> Neither wanted this Law parts of prudent and deep fore-ſight, for it did the better take away occaſion for the People to buſie themſelves to prie into the King's Title, for that however it fell, their Safety was provided for. Beſides, it could not but greatly draw unto him the love and hearts of the People, becauſe he ſeemed more careful for them than for himſelf.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Cook, p.</hi> 7. in the Third Book of <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> on the word <hi>Le Roy,</hi> ſpeaking of Treaſon, ſays, <hi>That the Act for Treaſon is to be underſtood of a King in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Crown and Kingdom, for if there be a King regnant in poſſeſſion, although he be</hi> Rex de facto <hi>only, and not</hi> de Jure, <hi>yet is he King within the purview of this Statute.</hi> And the other that hath Right, and is out of poſſeſſion, is not within this Statute: And if Treaſon be committed againſt a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93052:27"/>
                  <hi>de jure,</hi> and after the King <hi>de jure</hi> cometh to the Crown, he ſhall puniſh the Treaſon againſt the King <hi>de facto;</hi> and a Pardon granted by the King <hi>de jure,</hi> that is not alſo King <hi>de facto,</hi> is void. It is the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all Lawyers, that <hi>in rebus dubiis melior eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio poſſidentis.</hi> Judge <hi>Hales</hi> gives the ſame ſenſe of that Statute, in his Remarks on the Pleas of the Crown, Chapter of Treaſon.</p>
               <p>Now both theſe were great Lawyers, and wrote un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch as were Kings <hi>de jure,</hi> and in peaceable times. The Argument then is this: If <hi>Treaſon</hi> may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt a King in poſſeſſion, or <hi>de facto,</hi> and not againſt the King <hi>de jure,</hi> being out of the poſſeſſion, then I owe Allegiance to the King in poſſeſſion, and not to the King out of poſſeſſion, though King <hi>de jure.</hi> The Rule of the Law is this, <hi>I owe Allegiance</hi> to him that gives me Protection, whether I live at home un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a King <hi>de facto,</hi> or live as a Stranger abroad under one that is a King <hi>de jure.</hi> I owe Allegiance unto each while I am under their Protection; for thus in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe, Seventh Book of <hi>Cook</hi>'s Reports; one <hi>Shirly</hi> a <hi>French-man,</hi> and ſome Subjects of the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> having conſpired with <hi>Lopez</hi> for the death of the Queen, were Indicted for acting <hi>contra Legiantiae ſuae debitum,</hi> againſt their due Allegiance, and were found Guilty, and Executed. And this the Law calls a local Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance. When Cities and Souldiers are taken in War, they may, to preſerve their Lives, ſwear to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror never to bear Arms againſt him; by which Oath the condition of their former Prince is no way made worſe, for had they refuſed ſuch an Oath, they ſhould have loſt their Lives, which by this means being preſerved, they may be in a condition to ſerve their Prince in any thing elſe but in fighting againſt him
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93052:28"/>who ſpared his Liſe. Beſides it is well known, that many good and wholeſome Laws were made by ſuch as were Kings only <hi>de facto,</hi> not <hi>de jure,</hi> which are ſtill in force with us as they were with the Subjects that lived in their ſeveral Reigns; whence it follows, that we owe and ought to yield Allegiance to the King <hi>de facto,</hi> and obſerve his Laws, and to Pray for him as King. On the Depoſing of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, in a Provincial Synod in <hi>Canterbury</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, whoſe Title was only <hi>de facto,</hi> it was decreed, that Prayers ſhould be made <hi>pro ipſius &amp; Regni ſalute,</hi> as he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. And <hi>Arundel,</hi> then Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> tells the King, that the Clergy did <hi>pugnare precibus &amp; ſacrificiis apud deum pro victoriis ei obtinendis. Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wolfe, Anno</hi> 854. was made King while his Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was living, yet <hi>Elſton</hi> and <hi>Swithon,</hi> Biſhops, prayed ſolemnly for him: So the Biſhops prayed for <hi>Will. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi> his elder Brother living. St. <hi>Anſelme</hi> alſo, though baniſhed by <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, did him Homage, and prayed for him. And although our five firſt Kings, beginning at <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, came irregularly to the Crown: The firſt by Conqueſt, the ſecond and third while their elder Brother lived, the fourth reigned when his Predeceſſor had a Daughter living, which was <hi>Maude</hi> the Empreſs; the fifth while his Mother, the right Heir, was living, yet were the ſtated Forms of Prayers ſtill continued in the Ancient Miſſals re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.</p>
               <p>Nor can we well be exceſſive in our deference to thoſe who under God have been the chief Inſtruments of the Common Safety; for if the Law of Nature, which obligeth every particular perſon to ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and much more to the preſervation of the Publick Welfare, (in which caſe we may <hi>vim in repellere</hi>) be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93052:28"/>prior and paramont to any ſubſequent Law of a more private concern, we of this Nation, which were ſo near to deſtruction, had all reaſon imaginable, to ſecure our ſelves againſt ſuch violent and illegal attempts as were made, not only againſt our ſelves, but againſt the whole Proteſtant intereſt throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch dreadful inſtances of Perſecution in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nations of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piedmont;</hi> for the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not, whether we ſhould chuſe Sin rather than Affliction, in which caſe the Apoſtle hath determined, <hi>that we may not do evil, that good may come of it;</hi> but whether of two temporal evils, the leaſt is to be choſen, or whether, when we are left without a Governor, we ſhould ſet a Bramble over us, to rent and tare our fleſh, or the healing Olive, under whoſe branches we might ſet down in peace and ſecurity. It is very obſervable, what God ſays concerning <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> the wicked Son (of a good Father) <hi>Joſiah, Jer.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Shalt thou reign, becauſe thou cloſest thy ſelf in Cedar? did not thy Father eat and drink and do juſtice and judgment, and then it was well with him? But thine eyes and thy heart are not but for thy covetouſneſs to ſhed innocent blood, and for oppreſſion and violence to do it, therefore thus ſaith the Lord concerning Jehoiakim, the ſon of Joſiah King of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, they ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, Ah Lord, or, Ah his Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore leave it to the ſerious conſideration of my Brethren, whether it be more eligible, to pray for them in our Liturgy, who have preſerved us in the free uſe of it, or for ſuch as would have taken it from us, and impoſed the Maſs book and Legends, inſtead of that and the Scriptures, by which we ſhould have been reduced to this <hi>dilemma,</hi> either we muſt obey, to the violation of our Conſcience, or, for our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93052:29"/>we and our Families muſt be utterly deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>If yet upon conſideration of what hath been here ſaid, and what our own judgments may add, we are ſtill in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> and do doubt to whom the Title of the Crown doth of right belong. I doubt not but the Law of Charity to our ſelves, our Families, and love to the Proteſtant Religion, may be of great weight to turn the Scales, and warrant our reſolution in a caſe ſo doubtful.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon, Praelect.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 176. puts this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>When any one takes the Government on him, having by force driven out the lawful Prince, or ſo ſtreightned him, that he cannot purſue his right, which is invaded, not on a doubtful right, but by manifest wrong, what ſhall a good Subject, that hath ſworn Allegiance to the oppreſſed Prince, do in this Caſe?</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>It ſeems to me, that it is not only lawful for a good Subject to obey the Laws of the Prince in being, and to do what he is commanded, modo non ſit factu turpe aut injuſtum,</hi> if the thing be not in it ſelf evil or unjuſt. <hi>But alſo, that if the condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affairs require it, there may be a neceſſity of obeying, or he may be judged to fail of his duty;</hi> and whereas he had ſaid, that Laws made by him that wanted lawful power, did not bind in Conſcience, he anſwers, <hi>that theſe things are not repugnant, becauſe though the Subject be bound to do what the Law requires, yet he is not bound to that Law, but to himſelf and his Country.</hi> The Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is annexed to the Law that concerns himſelf and is truly a Law, which he thus explains: <hi>Seeing it is the duty of a pious and prudent man, to conſider not only what is lawful, but what becomes him, and may be expedient to others, a good Subject may be bound to do that for the welfare of himſelf and fellow ſubjects, to which by Law he is not bound, which obligation ariſeth from the duty he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93052:29"/>oweth to himſelf and to his Country, that Wars and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines may be prevented, and we may live peaceable under them, without violating the Faith we owe to the rightful Heir.</hi> But then he raiſeth the Queſtion, <hi>Seeing no man can ſerve two Maſters, eſpecially of contrary interest, how can we pleaſe the one, without diſpleaſing the other?</hi> His Anſwer is, <hi>It may be preſumed, that the rightful Prince will conſent, becauſe the Subject herein doth not ſo much ſerve the Poſſeſſor as the Common-wealth, the ſafety whereof no leſs concerns the injured Prince, than the preſent Poſſeſſor, and probably more, for as the true Mother of the Child had greater tenderneſs of its life than the pretended Mother, ſo the true Prince may be preſumed to have a greater regard to the welfare of the People, than the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Claudian <hi>to</hi> Honorius.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tu civem patrem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> geris tu conſule cunctis</l>
                  <l>Non tibi, nec tua te moveant ſed publica vota.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As a Mariner is ſuppoſed to intend the guiding of his Ship to a ſafe Harbor, and a Phyſician to intend the Health of his Patient, ſo is a Prince preſumed to intend the proſperity of his People, which is the great end of Government.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> goes farther; ſpeaking of the Roman Cruelties, ſays, <hi>They are ſuch as are able to ſet good men at their wits end, and make them juſtly doubt, ſince you refuſe the courſe of all good Laws, Divine and Humane, whether by the Law of Nature they may not defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves against ſuch barbarous blood ſuckers.</hi> For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is attempted on us without Law, is force, and we may, <hi>vim vi repellere,</hi> as in the caſe of a Sheriff taking
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93052:30"/>poſſeſſion on a Judgment; if a Prince ſhould commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion armed men to oppoſe him in the execution of his Office, he may lawfully reſiſt them, and the Law doth indempnifie him; the Princes Private Will cannot make void his Publick Will, formerly declared and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his Laws.</p>
               <p>This hath been the ſence and practice of our own and other Proteſtant Nations; of our own in the Caſe of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> who brought <hi>French</hi> Forces into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to withſtand the Reformation, endeavoured by the Nobles: the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> gave a Subſidy of 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> in the Pound, to defray the Charge of that War, and call it, her uſing all prudent and Godly means, 5 <hi>Eliz. ch.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp; ch.</hi> 27. The Temporalty call it, <hi>The princely and upright preſervation of the Liberty of the Realm and Nation of</hi> Scotland <hi>from eminent Captivity and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And for abating Hoſtility and Perſecution with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> there were Forces ſent under the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> to <hi>New-haven,</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, which was then accounted a Godly and prudent means to abate Hoſtility and Perſecution, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt the Profeſſors of God's Holy Goſpel. And in the 35 of <hi>Eliz. ch.</hi> 12. was another Subſidy granted by the Clergy for the Queen's Charges, in the prudent and needful prevention of ſuch Attempts as tended to the Extirpation of the ſincere Profeſſion of the Goſpel both here and elſewhere. And <hi>Ch.</hi> 13. the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty gave this Reaſon for their Subſidy. <hi>Beſides the great and perpetual Honour which it hath pleaſed God to give your Majeſty abroad, in making you the principal Support of all Juſt and Religious Cauſes againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, beſides the great Succours in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Flanders, <hi>which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93052:30"/>we conceive to be moſt Honourable in regard of the ancient League, the Juſtice and Equity of the Cauſes,</hi> &amp;c. And in 39 <hi>Eliz. ch.</hi> 27. they ſay, <hi>This Land is become, ſince your Majeſty's days, both a Port and Haven of Refuge for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed States and Kingdoms, and a Rock and Bulwark of Oppoſition againſt the Tyranny and ambitious Attempts of mighty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping Potentates.</hi> And in 43 <hi>Eliz. ch.</hi> 17. The Clergy ſay, <hi>Who hath, or ſhould have a livelier ſenſe or better remembrance of your Majeſty's Princely Courage and Conſtancy in advancing and protecting the free Profeſſion of the Goſpel within and without your Majeſty's Dominions, than your Clergy?</hi> And we cannot doubt but they would have acted the ſame thing for their own Preſervation, which they approved and encouraged others to do.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtants of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Lantgrave,</hi> being ſeven Princes, and Twenty four Cities, declare, <hi>That the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror was reciprocally bound to them as they to him; and that he had diſſolved their Obligation of Allegiance by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of their Poſſeſſions, and endeavouring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Religion, which unjuſt Attempts have not God for their Author: Nor are we otherwiſe bound to</hi> Caeſar <hi>than on his performing the Conditions on which he was created</hi> Caeſar, <hi>Sleidan, lib.</hi> 18. The <hi>Magdeburg</hi> Divines affirm the ſame, <hi>Sleidan, l.</hi> 22. <hi>Where the Laws and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Government allow of a defence, the Goſpel doth ſo too, for it doth not alter the Laws of a State;</hi> which may be an Anſwer to what is urged from <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. for the Obligation of all Subjects is ſuch, as the Laws under which they live do require. The Oath of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Poland</hi> hath this <hi>Salvo</hi> in the Oath of the King; <hi>Quod ſi Sacramentum meum violavero incolae Regni mei nullam nobis obedientiam praeſtare tenebuntur.</hi> In <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Second's time, the Parliament declared in a Statute of <hi>Praemunire, That the Crown of</hi> England <hi>hath
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93052:31"/>been ſo free</hi> (i. e.) from the Incroachments of the Pope) <hi>at all times, that it hath been in no Earthly Subjection, but immediately ſubject to God in all things touching the Regal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Crown; and God defend</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that it ſhould be ſubmitted to the Pope, and the Laws and Statutes of the Realm be by him defeated and avoided at his pleaſure in perpetual deſtruction of the Soveraignty of the King, his Crown and Dignity, and of all the Realm; and therefore they declare, That they and all the Leige Commons of the Realm will ſtand with their Lord the King and his Crown and Regalty in the caſes aforeſaid</hi> (viz. purchaſing of Bulls from <hi>Rome,</hi> executing Judgments given in that Court, Tranſlating of Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>and in all other caſes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted againſt him, and his Crown, and Regalty, in all points to live and to dye. And they pray the King, and him require by way of Juſtice, to Examine all the Lords in Parliament, as well Spiritual as Temporal, ſeverally, and all the Eſtates of the Parliament, how they think of the cauſes aforeſaid, which be ſo openly againſt the King's Crown, and in derogation of his Regalty, and how they will ſtand with the King in upholding the Rights of the ſaid Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> And we find by a Letter of King <hi>John</hi>'s to the Pope, That if the King would, yet the Barons would not ſubmit to King or Pope in thoſe caſes. How contrary to this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Praemunire</hi> did they act, that inſtead of a ſtrict en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after ſuch as endeavoured to ſubject the Nation to the Uſurpations of <hi>Rome,</hi> did cloſely and particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine both Lords and Commons, whether they would ſubmit to the introducing that Uſurpation, and upon their Refuſal, were preſently diſcharged of their reſpective Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and excluded from the Prince's favour: Was not this to ſubvert a <hi>Fundamental Conſtitution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> And by that Act, to incur a <hi>Praemunire. Carpzorius,</hi> an approved Author, <hi>de Capital. Caeſarea,</hi> ſays, <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 15.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93052:31"/>
                  <hi>There is no King or Supreme Prince in the Chriſtian World, whoſe Power ſome certain Compact made with the ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the People, may not reſtrain and limit, and which are not bound by the Capitulation. Reinkinck</hi> ſays the ſame of the Emperor, <hi>de Reg. Secul. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Claſſ.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>That</hi> Caeſar <hi>the Head of the Empire, is bound by the Laws;</hi> and how ſhould the King of <hi>England</hi> be above all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings? It was too much for him to aſpire to be like the moſt Chriſtian King. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt acknowledged, <hi>That if he would (ſubmit to the Pope) his Nobles would not permit it.</hi> And the Lords and Commons under <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, ſignified to the Pope (concerning his claim to <hi>Scotland</hi>) <hi>that they neither ought nor would permit it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the King ſhould attempt it.</hi> And under <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, it is recorded, <hi>That if the King and Nobles ſhould agree to it, yet the Commons would not permit the entrance of</hi> Adomer, <hi>the Pope's Legate, into</hi> England. <hi>Bodmin,</hi> treating of the King of <hi>France</hi> (ſays) <hi>Principem contra leges nil poſſe, &amp; reſcriptis ejus nullam rationem haberi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere niſi aequitate perinde &amp; veritati conſentanea ſint. Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton,</hi> of the King of <hi>England,</hi> ſays, <hi>Rex eſt ſub lege quia Lex facit Regem.</hi> This <hi>Bracton,</hi> who lived in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, was of the judgment, <hi>That the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons had a power to reſtrain the Kings Exorbitances,</hi> lib. 3. ch. 26. <hi>Rex habet ſuperiorem deum item legem per quam factus eſt Rex, item Curiam ſuam</hi> (viz.) <hi>Comites &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones ſuos.</hi> The Barons proceeded in their Wars on this Principle, <hi>That they had a power to reſtrain their Kings from ſubverting the Laws and Religion eſtabliſhed.</hi> And what Opinion the Religious Men of that Time had of thoſe Wars, may appear by the Opinion that the Chronicle of <hi>Mailros</hi> had of <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Monfort,</hi> of which I have ſpoken before. This may ſuffice to reſolve the Conſcience in reſpect of the Law.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:93052:32"/>
               <p>Thus have I given an Account of the Judgment of many learned Men concerning the <hi>Queries</hi> propoſed. How far they may prevail with others I cannot preſage. But I plainly perceive, that many very learned and good Men are yet of another Opinion; and indeed there are many very difficult Arguments, both from Scripture and Laws, which by the ſeveral Interpretations given of them by learned Men of this and former Ages, may confirm them in their prejudices. Therefore my humble Requeſt to them that are yet unſatisfied, is, That laying aſide all Prejudices, they would maturely conſider of the Arguments <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> and after diligent Enquiry, and hearty Prayers, follow the dictates of a well-informed Conſcience,
<q>
                     <l>— Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
                     <l>Candidus imperti ſi non his utere mecum.</l>
                  </q> In the mean time let the Apoſtle's Rule be obſerved by the Parties of different Perſuaſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he gives in the Chapter immediately after the Rules for Obedience; <hi>Him that is weak in the faith, receive, but not to doubtful diſputations, for one believeth that he may eat all things; another, who is weak, eateth herbs. Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not: And let not him that eateth not deſpiſe him that eateth. Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93052:32"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THE Arguments that have been propoſed, may prevail with ſome perſons to alter their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning their Obligations to the late King, and if ſo, they will be ſenſible of the neceſſity of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring their Duty to the Eſtabliſhed Government, which they may do with all cheerfulneſs and confidence of Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Favour; for their preſent Majeſties cannot but judge, that they who were ſo conſcientiouſly Dutiful to the late King, while he kept his Station among them, tho' he induſtriouſly ſought to Ruine them as to their Civil and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Intereſts, and were doubtful how they might Deſert him when he had abandoned and deſerted them; I ſay, they cannot but judge, upon their ingaging to be true and faithful to them who have redeemed them from Slavery and Popery, and have adventured all their Subſtance, and their very Lives, that they might ſecure to them their Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Religion, which doubtleſs they will make their chief buſineſs, becauſe it is their intereſt ſo to do.</p>
            <p>As to ſuch who having weighed theſe Arguments, are yet in <hi>Aequilibrio,</hi> and doubt whether the late King or their preſent Majeſties have the better right; in ſuch a caſe a man is to act according to his reaſon and diſcretion; and then tho' he may be miſtaken, yet his miſtake is pardonable; now his diſcretion will teach him to recollect all the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies and Miſeries that will moſt probably follow on his refuſal to ſubmit to the preſent Government, if he ſtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the intereſt of the late King, and he ſhould prove ſucceſsful, then in all probability he will intail Popery and Slavery, not only on himſelf and Family, but on the whole Nation for ſucceeding Ages, and on the Proteſtant Nations throughout all <hi>Europe;</hi> whereas if he live in due Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Eſtabliſhed Government; in conjunction with the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93052:33"/>Body of the Nation, and ſtudy to be quiet, and to do his own buſineſs, following Peace and Holineſs, all thoſe Evils may be prevented, and the Lord will bleſs our <hi>Sion,</hi> and we may ſee the good of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> all the days of our Life; yea, <hi>we may ſee our childrens children, and peace upon all the Iſrael of GOD.</hi> Theſe Conſiderations ought to turn the Scales which hung in equal ballance before. To ſuch a doubting perſon I ſhall propoſe this Caſe; Suppoſe a perſon that hath been given to Quarrels and Brawels found dead, and ſome wounds and bruiſes found by Inqueſt on his body, whereby it is preſumed that he was murdered, and a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his, a perſon of a ſober and peaceable converſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known to have been in his company near the time and place where he was found dead, is arrained for the Murder, but no Evidence of the matter of Fact produced againſt him, only ſome probable Circumſtances, the queſtion is, whether a Jury man that hath only ſome Circumſtances to guide him in his Verdict, may find ſuch a perſon Guilty of that Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which if he do, he may draw the Guilt of ſhedding In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood on himſelf, and undo a Neighbour's Family; I think an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> would be more juſtifiable than a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Guilt. Where the caſe is dubious, we ſhould chooſe that part which infers the leaſt danger, in caſe we ſhould err, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays, and thence he concludes, <hi>It is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Abſolve the Guilty, than to Condemn the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. And,</hi> Minus malum rationem induit boni. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus dubiis pars tutior eligenda. I know that Biſhop <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi> in his <hi>Judicium, Ox.</hi> p. <hi>44.</hi> hath determined, <hi>That when a King is hindred from protecting his People,</hi> (Culpa non ſua ſed alienâ nec voluntatis defectu ſed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatis.) <hi>for want of Power, we are not freed from our Allegiance,</hi> but in caſe there is not only a defect of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to protect us, but a plain declaration of a Will to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, this will plainly overthrow that determination, as the Biſhop himſelf hath in other of his Writings done: <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93052:33"/>deſunt judicia incipit bellum.</hi> And it is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that the Biſhop wrote this in the Caſe of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, from which this of <hi>James</hi> the Second differs <hi>toto caelo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To thoſe that are not yet reconciled to the now Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Government, I ſhall offer theſe Conſiderations:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether the preſent King had not a just cauſe for Invading the Kingdom. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether having In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded it, and obtained a full and peaceable Poſſeſſion by a general conſent of the People, he hath obtained a rightful Title. The Cauſes that do juſtifie the Invaſion are theſe: <hi>1.</hi> The Vindication of his Lady's Title, which was in a manner endeavoured to be raviſhed from her by a Prince whoſe Birth was ſo much ſuſpected, and whereof the Nation was ſo generally convinced. <hi>2.</hi> The Invitation of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Lords Spiritual and Temporal, with many Commons, groaning under an Arbitrary Power, Popery and Slavery, for which cauſe many Lords and Commons had left the Kingdom, and ſought protection from the preſent King, and came in with him. <hi>3.</hi> The preſent King was made the Head of the Proteſtant Party by thoſe Princes who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the Defence of the Reformed Religion againſt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Princes that had confederated to root it out; and a better method could not be taken, than to begin with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> where, if the deſigns for Popery had ſucceeded, the Proteſtant Cauſe had been almoſt deſparate, which is now in a hopeful way of Eſtabliſhment: Theſe Cauſes are ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to juſtifie the Invaſion, that I think no good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant will doubt of them; and as little doubt can be made of the ſecond Conſideration, that he who on ſuch juſt Grounds Invades a Kingdom, and having gotten a full and quiet Poſſeſſion, is by the general Conſent of the People accepted and declared their King, hath a lawful Right and Title, for first, <hi>Ubi deſinunt judicia incipit bellum;</hi> and as Law Suits, ſo War, may be waged for prevention of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93052:34"/>not yet done; As <hi>Livy</hi> ſays, <hi>Juſtum eſt bellum quod neceſſarium eſt &amp; pia Arma quibus nulla niſi in armis relinquitur ſpes;</hi> When it is manifeſt our ſitting ſtill will make our Condition worſe, we may adventure on the danger of War. The War was begun by the <hi>French</hi> King and his Confederates againſt the Prince; <hi>England</hi> was like to be in the Confederacy by what the King acted and endeavoured againſt the Proteſtant Religion: And, <hi>Tune tua res Agitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the firſt Cauſe that Juſtifies the War on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King's part; the ſecond Cauſe is, the Recovery of the Right which his Lady and himſelf had to the Succeſſion, which was in a manner taken from them; <hi>Grotius de Jure Belli,</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>2. De rebus repetendis,</hi> proves this at large in a conſiderable Paragraph to which I refer the Reader: And of this I ſhall give but one or two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances among many in the Scriptures. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s War on the King of <hi>Elam</hi> who had ſpoiled <hi>Sodom,</hi> was juſt, <hi>Gen. 14.</hi> And ſo were the Wars of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the <hi>Aſſirians</hi> and other Nations that invaded their Dominion, and would have kept them from them, of this there can be no doubt; nor can, ſecondly, the Vindication of a People oppreſſed by their Prince, againſt the Laws of God and the Land; if a Father ſeek the deſtruction of an innocent perſon, his Son may piouſly reſtrain his Father from that act which would not only ruine the innocent in this World, but himſelf in the World to come. So that this War for the aſſerting the Title of the Prince and Princeſs to the Crown, and for the defence of our Religion, againſt the Confederacy of Popiſh Princes to extirpate it, (which is matter of Fact) may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear moſt Just; for tho' Religion may not be propagated by Arms, yet it may be defended where it is Eſtabliſhed by Law, againſt forreign Powers that conſpire the deſtruction of it: <hi>Grotius</hi> l <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> n. <hi>4.</hi> approves a War on behalf of Confederates, <hi>For he that doth not repel an Injury from
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93052:34"/>his Confederates if he can, is as much in fault as he that doth the Injury.</hi> He commends <hi>Conſtantine</hi> for making War on <hi>Maxentius</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi> who perſecuted ſuch of their Subjects as were Chriſtians, only for their Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> n. <hi>39. Injuries begun only, are not to be vindicated by Arms, unleſs the matter be both very weighty, and be already proceeded ſo far, that from what is already done, either a certain miſchief, tho' not yet what was intended, hath already befallen, or ſome extraordinary danger do threaten thereby. If an Enemy hath once aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted me, and comes armed with a reſolution to kill me, I am not to tarry till he comes within reach of me, and receive his Weapons upon my naked breaſt, but ſeaſonably to prevent him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>l. 2. c. 25. n. 8. Thoſe Princes who are free, may make War for themſelves or others: And tho' we ſhould grant, that Subjects might not take Arms for their own Defence againſt their Prince, no not in caſe of greateſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> (which yet is doubted even by thoſe whoſe purpoſe it was to defend Regal Power) <hi>yet it follows not, that other Princes may not take Arms in their defence; that which is unlawful for one to do for himſelf, by reaſon of a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal impediment, may be lawful for another to do for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As in Affairs of the Church the Biſhops are ſaid to take on them the care of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, ſo beſide the care of their particular Dominions, Kings aſſume the general care of Humane Societies. <hi>Seneca</hi> reſolves, <hi>Bello a me peti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt qui a mea gente ſepoſitus ſuam exagitat.</hi> And <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, That War ſhould be undertaken only that we may live in Peace, and not be injured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be objected, That God will take care of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Deorum injuriae diis curae &amp; perjurium ſatis habet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ultorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> So it may be ſaid of other Sins which God will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93052:35"/>puniſh, yet the Laws are juſtly executed on the Offenders by the Magiſtrate, as all grant.</p>
            <p>And if it be objected, That ſuch Offences are puniſhed not ſo much as committed againſt God, as for the damage done to men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is obſerved, that not only ſuch Offences are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by men, as are directly committed againſt other men, but ſuch as by conſequence may be prejudicial to others, as Self-murder, <hi>Sodomy, &amp;c.</hi> for tho' the principal end be to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure God's favour, (by puniſhing ſuch Crimes) yet it is done alſo to prevent the influence and notable effects on Humane Societies. See <hi>l. 2. c. 20. n. 44.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be farther objected, That if we wholly forſake the King, we ſhall juſtifie the Rebellion againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who was charged with deſigns of bringing in Popery and Arbitrary Government, Illegal Impoſitions, Evil Counſellors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſuppoſe the Objectors that are ſo tender of commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any act of Diſloyalty againſt King <hi>James</hi> the Second, will by no means approve of what was done againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; but they are afraid of the reproach and ſcandal, as if they did allow of that by doing the like. But the Caſe is extreamly different, the one King being a well-reſolved Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, the other a ſeduced Papiſt; <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt gave as great aſſurances of his conſtancy in the Proteſtant Religion, by taking the Holy Sacrament publickly, and purpoſely for the ſatisfaction of his Subjects, by diſputing for it againſt Papiſts, by charging his Children against it a little before his death, and even then giving a full Teſtimony of dying in it: But <hi>James</hi> the Second, contrary to his Education, and his Royal Father's Charge, deſerted that Religion, eſpouſed Popery, and reſolved to introduce it to his Kingdom, which he deſerted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then he would forego that deſign: His Father lost his life to preſerve the Church and the Eſtabliſhed Religion, which King <hi>James</hi> induſtriouſly ſought to deſtroy, and in fact
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93052:35"/>he had deſtroyed the Government Eſtabliſhed before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Kingdom. <hi>2ly,</hi> There was a great diſparity in their actions; tho' <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was unhappily forced from the full Adminiſtration of the Government, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his Loyal Subjects, yet he kept within the Kingdom, and endeavoured to aſſert his and his Peoples Rights, not by the Sword only, but by many Treaties and gracious Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch as ſatisfied all ſober perſons even among his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, as by their too late Votes on that behalf appeared: He did not declare that he was Abſolute, and expected O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Commands, without any Reſerve; he did not Impriſon his Biſhops only for Petitioning in a matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as <hi>James</hi> the Second, and the Enemies of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt did; Fears and Jealouſies, or very light Impoſitions on the People for urgent Neceſſities, were made the Ground of the War against <hi>Charles</hi> the First; but real and intollerable Greivances, ſuch as the Subjects could not bear, nor knew how to remove. <hi>3ly,</hi> There is a great diſparity in the adverſe Parties, <hi>Charles</hi> the First was oppoſed by his Subjects, <hi>James</hi> the Second by a free Prince to aſſert a just Right; the better part of <hi>Charles</hi> the First's Subjects adhered to him, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him, and at length the whole body of the Nation being convinced of the Injuſtice of the War, recalled <hi>Charles</hi> the Second to ſucceed his Father: And I hope no man will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Benefits we have received by the preſent King's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, with the Miſchiefs that we endured, and expected greater not only from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers on <hi>Charles</hi> the First, but the tranſactions of <hi>James</hi> the Second. And ſuch perſons do as ſurely deſerve, as they will draw on themſelves that Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Slavery which they abhor, who are not ſatisfied with that happy Deliverance which they now injoy, and by their Thankfulneſs and Obedience to God and the King, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to them and their Poſterity; ſo that I am well perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they who ingaged againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the First, were highly criminal, and that they who (ſince <hi>James</hi> the Second
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93052:36"/>deſerted the Kingdom) ſhall ingage for him, are really pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> Conſideration is, Whether the King having on theſe grounds begun a War, and gotten quiet poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, and by the People (acknowledging the Right of his Lady to the Succeſſion on the Vacancy by Deſertion) are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King and Queen, have a juſt Title, and ſuch as we ought to ſwear Allegiance to As to the Vacancy of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I have ſaid enough already, and all will grant, that if a Crown be Forfeitable, ours was forfeited: Now in caſe of this Vacancy, the Right of Succeſſion by our Laws is in the next Heir, which is the preſent Queen, and that ſhe ought immediately to ſucceed, (becauſe by a Maxim in our Laws, the King never dies) and the ſole Adminiſtration is to be in her, and therefore it is objected, That we cannot ſwear Faith and true Allegiance to any other. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Seeing all Oaths and Acts that oblige the Subjects are in the name of the Queen as well as of the King, we pay our Obedience where it is due; and this may ſatisfie the Conſcience of every one, as to our preſent Condition at leaſt, until there be a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made. And if the ſole Power ſhould be devolved on the preſent King, the conſent of the next Heir being obtained, to whom is the Injury done? Not to the Princeſs <hi>Anne,</hi> for <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti non fit injuria;</hi> not to the People for the ſame reaſon, they having expreſſed their conſent; but this hath its Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, as is already ſaid.</p>
            <p>If in diſcuſſing the Right of Succeſſion, a queſtion do ariſe concerning the Primary Will and Intention of the People at the firſt Inſtitution of a Kingdom, it is not amiſs to take the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the preſent People, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> of the Nobles, Clergy, and Commons, as <hi>Cambden</hi> ſays, of <hi>England, Anno 1571, 1572. Grotius</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> n. <hi>27.</hi> And the Equity of it ſeemeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that he who redeemed the Crown may wear it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People, and the conſent of the right Heir; nor can the People be blamed for joyning in ſuch conſent, becauſe it hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93052:36"/>been thought a Duty in Gratitude, that ſuch Heroes as have vindicated a People from Thraldom, and become great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors to them, have been by conſent of the People ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged their Kings. So <hi>Ariſtotle Polit.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> n. <hi>89.</hi> And in ſuch a juncture of Affairs, the whole Proteſtant Cauſe lying at ſtake, the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> being poſſeſſed by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and many Diviſions in our own Nation, there is need of more than the Authority of a ſingle perſon. The Act of <hi>13</hi> of <hi>Eliz.</hi> aſſerts it to be in the Power of the Parliament to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or limit the Succeſſion. And as to matter of fact, ſuch alteration hath been made, for in the Caſes of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Succeſſion was altered, becauſe one of them was Illegitimate: Again, <hi>Quod fieri non debuit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Valet;</hi> The neceſſity of Affairs that inforc'd it, may ſpeak much in defence of it; As <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſubmitting to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, <hi>That having ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, they ought not to make reſiſtance.</hi> And if by tract of time, an Empire which was unjuſtly acquired, may juſtly be ſubmitted to, becauſe of an implicite Conſent of the People to ſuch an Empire, I ſee no cauſe but the expreſs actual Conſent of a People, to a Prince, may juſtly oblige them. Such a Conſent of the Senate and People to the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, was the ground of our Saviour's Injunction for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribute, and of the Apoſtles requiring Subjection to them: And ſo we may conclude, as <hi>Huſhai</hi> did, <hi>2 Sam. 16.18. Whom the LORD and this People, and all the Men of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>ſhall chooſe, his will I be, and with him I will abide.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
